<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The libertie of the subject against the pretended power of impositions. Maintained by an argument in Parliament an[o]. 7[o]. Jacobi Regis. / By William Hakevvil of Lincolns Inne Esq.</title>
            <author>Hakewill, William, 1574-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E170_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873497</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873497</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157030</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86390)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E170[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The libertie of the subject against the pretended power of impositions. Maintained by an argument in Parliament an[o]. 7[o]. Jacobi Regis. / By William Hakevvil of Lincolns Inne Esq.</title>
                  <author>Hakewill, William, 1574-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 142, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "William .. Esq." are enclosed in brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Bracketed "o" in title is in superscript.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taxation --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Constitutional law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157030:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157030:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIBERTIE OF THE Subject: AGAINST THE PRETENDED POWER OF IMPOSITIONS.</p>
            <p>Maintained by an Argument in Parliament <hi>An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> JACOB 1 <hi>Regis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM HAKEVVIL of <hi>Lincolns Inne</hi> Eſq.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. H. An. Dom.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:157030:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157030:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing very ſenſible of a great Injury lately done mee, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme falſe printing of a ſmal Treatiſe of my Compoſing, ſtoln out without my conſent, and hearing accidentally that ſome part of this alſo had paſſed the Preſſe, I thought good for the preventing of the like wrong to ſtay the forwardneſſe of the printer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I had reviewed and corrected it by mine owne Notes. For my part, I ſhould have been contented altogether to have reſtrained it, if I might, But now ſeeing it muſt abroad, I ſhall not bee aſhamed to let it beare my name, and owne the errors of it my ſelf (thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:157030:3"/> of the Preſſe excepted) though hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had gayned ſo much reputation by ſome, as it was attributed to a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier Author. Some there are yet ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving that heard this Argument about thirty yeeres ſince in the <hi>Commons-Houſe</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> but it hath now exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it ſelfe beyond the probable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of a Speech or Argument, by the inſertion of many Records and Acts of Parliament more at large, which at the delivery of it, were but meerely quoted.</p>
            <p>The Endeavour of it is to prove that the juſt Prerogative of our Kings never warranted them to raiſe monies at their pleaſure, by laying a charge on Merchandize to bee Exported or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, without aſſent of Parliament. But, on the contrary, the ſetled Lawes of the Land, the Preſidents of former Ages, the Acts of our moſt neceſſitous and powerfull Princes, and indeed eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing requiſite to make the Truth
<pb facs="tcp:157030:3"/> apparent, doe as it were unanimouſly conſent to diſcharge us of this unjuſt and heavy Burthen.</p>
            <p>And you ſhall ſee herein how the policy of active Princes hath by many waies attempted to undermine thoſe Fortifications which the wiſdom of our Anceſtors hath rayſed to maintaine themſelves from this kinde of Aſſault. You ſhall ſee with how great difficulty their prevailing was withſtood: And (which is the glory of Truth) you ſhall finde thoſe deſignes which were laid to overthrow our Right, mainly to make for the evidence and confirmation of it. For, whatever unjuſt Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were either exacted by a pretended lawfullneſſe, or ſet up by a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding power, were by complaint in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments preſently following taken down, and remain on Record as (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt themſelves) unlawfull, and againſt our Libertie.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons and Arguments of
<pb facs="tcp:157030:4"/> mine (how meane ſoever) thoſe times wherein I urged them, accepted favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably; and ſince, in their private paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in manuſcripts, were entertained in many judicious hands, which made mee ſomwhat enlarge the conceit that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had of them; And now ſeeing neceſſitie enforceth mee to make them more publique, I muſt adventure them to the cenſure of theſe nice times. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall (happily) they may be to ſome, prejudiciall I hope to none: In which confidence (having the leave of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) they have likewiſe my leave to goe abroad.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
               <signed>W. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:157030:4"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 THat there was ever ſome Cuſtome due to the King by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law. <hi>folio</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>2 That it was a ſum certaine by the Common-Law. <hi>folio</hi> 10.</item>
               <item>3 That all the Revenues which the Common Law giveth to the King (out of the intereſt of the Subject) are certaine, or reducea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a certainty by ſome legall courſe, and none left to the Kings pleaſure. <hi>folio</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>4 The reaſons why the Law requireth ſuch certainty in thoſe Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues which the King hath out of the intereſt of the Subject. <hi>folio</hi> 12.</item>
               <item>5 Examples of Revenues given by the Common Law to the King, out of the intereſt of the Subject, and that they are all certaine. <hi>folio</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>6 Anſwer to an Objection, that the King may lay Impoſitions upon extraordinary occaſions. <hi>folio</hi> 21.</item>
               <item>7 Arguments drawne from the actions of our Kings, that they had no power to impoſe. <hi>folio</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>8 Arguments drawn from the forbearance of our Kings to lay Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, notwithſtanding their urgent occaſions. <hi>folio</hi> 34.</item>
               <item>9 The difference between the Preſidents urged, of Impoſitions laid by the antient Kings, and thoſe which are now laid. <hi>folio</hi> 29.</item>
               <item>10 A particular anſwer to the Impoſition of <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> in the pound, laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Merchant-ſtrangers by <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> 31, <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>folio</hi> 42, 43.</item>
               <item>11 The urgent occaſions which <hi>Ed</hi> 2. had to lay Impoſitions, and yet how he forbore. <hi>folio</hi> 48.</item>
               <item>12 The ſeverall policies uſed by <hi>Ed</hi> 3. for the introducing of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Impoſing: 1. Impoſitions taken by colour of a voluntary Grant from Merchants, <hi>folio</hi> 49. 2 By way of diſpenſation wiih penall Lawes, <hi>folio</hi> 59. 3 By way of Ordinance in Parliament, <hi>folio</hi> 61. 4 By co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of a Loane by Merchants, <hi>folio</hi> 64. 5 By Grants of Merchants for Liberties granted to them, <hi>folio</hi> 65. 6 By expreſſe and direct comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>folio</hi> 66. with ſeverall anſweres to all theſe ſeverall wayes.</item>
               <item>13 In what Statutes Impoſitions are mentioned after <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. time, untill <hi>Qu. Maries;</hi> and upon what occaſions, and how to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted. <hi>folio</hi> 73.</item>
               <item>14 The ſignification of the words <hi>Impoſition, Toll, Maletolt, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuma &amp; Conſuetudo magna &amp; parva. folio</hi> 73, 103.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:157030:5"/>
               <item> 15 No Impoſition laid from <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. time till <hi>Qu. Maries. folio</hi> 78.</item>
               <item>16 What urgent occaſions all the Kings from <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. till <hi>Qu. Maries</hi> time, had to lay Impoſitions, and yet did it not. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. f. 79. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. f. 82. <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. f. 84. <hi>Hen</hi> 6. f. 85. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. f. 85. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. f. 86. <hi>Hen</hi> 8. f. 89. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6 f 92. with a Corolary of all thoſe times and occaſions. <hi>folio</hi> 92.</item>
               <item>17 The Impoſitions laid by <hi>Q. Mary,</hi> and how anſwered. <hi>folio</hi> 93.</item>
               <item>18 Admitting the Kings had power by the Common Law to lay Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, yet how they are barred by Statutes. <hi>folio</hi> 98.</item>
               <item>19 <hi>Magna Charta, cap.</hi> 30. urged againſt Impoſitions, and the obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made againſt it, anſwered. 1 Objection, That it extendeth onely to Merchant-ſtrangers, f. 100. 2 That it was made onely againſt Taxes within the Land, f. 101. 3 That by the exception in the end of the Statute, the Kings Prerogative is ſalved. <hi>folio</hi> 111.</item>
               <item>20 The Statute <hi>de Tallagio non concedendo</hi> urged, with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the objections made thereunto, <hi>folio</hi> 113. The expoſition of the words <hi>Tallage, Ayde, Subſidie. folio</hi> 112, 114.</item>
               <item>21 The Statute of 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. urged againſt Impoſitions, and cleered from Objections: 1 That it is againſt the exceſſe of Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and not againſt the Right, f. 115, 116. 2 That it is onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt Impoſitions on Woolls. <hi>folio</hi> 118.</item>
               <item>22 The Statute of 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. urged againſt Impoſitions, and cleered from Objections: 1 That it extendeth onely to Impoſitions within the Land, and not upon merchandizes, with an expoſition of the word <hi>Charge. folio</hi> 118, 121.</item>
               <item>23 Anſwers to the Reaſons urged in maintenance of Impoſitions: 1 That becauſe it cannot appeare that the ancient Cuſtomes were ſet by Parliament, therefore they were impoſed by the King. <hi>folio</hi> 125. The Antiquity of Parliaments. <hi>folio</hi> 128.</item>
               <item>24 Anſwer to the the ſecond Reaſon urged for Impoſitions, That the King may totally reſtraine importation and exportation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may reſtraine <hi>ſub modo</hi> by laying Impoſitions. <hi>folio</hi> 124, 125, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>25 Anſwer to the third Reaſon, That the Ports are the Kings, and that he may open and ſhut them on what conditions he pleaſeth. <hi>folio</hi> 136.</item>
               <item>26 Anſwer to the fourth Reaſon, That the King is bound to protect Merchants, and ſafeguard the Seas, and that therefore he may lay moderate Impoſitions, for raiſing of many to defray his charges. <hi>folio</hi> 138.</item>
               <item>27 Anſwer to the fifth objection, That all forreign Princes have power to impoſe; and if our King ſhould not have the like, it might be very inconvenient to this State. ibid.</item>
               <item>28 A ſummary Concluſion of the whole Argument. <hi>folio</hi> 141.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:157030:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. SPEAKER:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queſtion now in debate amongſt us, is, Whether his</hi> M<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>. <hi>may, by his</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Royall <hi>(without aſſent of Parliament) at his own will and pleaſure, lay a new Charge or Impoſition upon Merchandizes, to be brought into, or out of this Kingdome of</hi> England; <hi>and enforce Merchants to pay the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Muſt confeſſe, that when this Point was firſt ſtirred mongſt us, and that wee, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſeeke redreſſe for the exceſſe of the preſent Impoſitions, reſolved to proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by calling his Majeſties right of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into queſtion, I was very ſory: for I ſaw we were then in a faire way to have obteined a very great abatement of the Impoſitions that now
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:157030:6"/> are; and beſides, we had his Majeſties promiſe never to lay any more but in Parliament time, by the advice and free conſent of his Subjects, repayring hither from all parts of the Realme; This hope of a preſent eaſe, and gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for the time to come, gave me (I confeſſe) a full ſatisfaction; eſpecially, ſeeing I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently perſwaded that his Majeſties right to impoſe was very cleere and not to be diſputed, and that therfore by drawing into queſtion the right, wee might give his Majeſty juſt occaſion to withdraw from us his gracious purpoſe of the preſent abatement, as alſo his promiſe for the time to come: For Syr, when the Caſe of <hi>Bates</hi> (who as you know was called into queſtion for refuſing to pay the Impoſition laid upon <hi>Currans</hi>) was argued in the Exchequer, in which Caſe his Majeſties right to Impoſe, was ſolemnly diſputed (and there reſolved for his Majeſty) I was then preſent at all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both at the Bar and at the Bench; And I doe confeſſe that by the weighty and unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable reaſons (as I then conceived them) of thoſe grave and reverend Judges,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fl<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ming</hi> Ch. Bar. <hi>Clarke. Savil.</hi>
               </note> ſitting in their ſeate of Juſtice, I was much perſwaded; but by thoſe many records vouched by them, I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together overcome, and as it were vanquiſh't to yeeld to them; for Syr, <hi>Ratio ſuadet, Anthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas vincit:</hi> But though I were then, and when the Queſtion was firſt moved in this houſe, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry confident, yet as you ſhall perceive anon, I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:157030:6"/> was not very conſtant in that opinion; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (amongſt others) imployed by this houſe to make ſearch in the Exchequer for Records, which (by the practiſe of former ages) might guide our judgements in this weighty point, and having diligently collected the Arguments made in the Exchequer, and not only ſo, but compared my owne collections with Reports thereof made by divers other of my friends, &amp; finding that ſome of the Records urged in thoſe Arguments were untruly vouched (and many miſaplyed) I then began to ſtagger in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and preſently fell to examine the weight of the Reaſons which had been alledged, which in my poore cenſure, I found not of ſtrength ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient (without the full concurrence of cleere Preſidents of former times) to maintaine the Judgement given, or my Opinion grounded thereupon: And therefore (Syr) In love to the truth I did forſake my former opinion as erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, and do now embrace the contrary, that is, <hi>That his Majeſty hath no right to impoſe,</hi> and ſo am now become a convert. Thoſe Reaſons that moved mee thus to change, and the weakeneſſe which I diſcovered in the Reaſons alledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the opinion which I now hold; I will, with your patience, open unto you, and will therein follow the commandement of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Peter. Beeing converted, ſeeke to convert my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the Judgement in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157030:7"/> ſtanding yet in force, ſo often caſt as a block in our way, though I much reverence the perſons of thoſe yet living, and the memory of thoſe that are with God, who gave the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Yet ſeeing (as I hope I ſhall bee able e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently to prove) the ſame to bee againſt the great <hi>Charter</hi> of our Liberties, I can eſteeme no otherwiſe of it then the Statute of 25.<hi>Ed.</hi> 1. cap. 10. pronounceth of all ſuch Judgements, that is; that it is void and to be held for nought. Thus much I thought good to ſay by way of Preamble or Introduction to the matter: now (by your favors) I will enter into the debate of the Queſtion; in handling of which I will pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely avoid the repetition of any thing that hath been ſpoken by any man that hath argued before, as knowing in what preſence I ſpeake. That I may the better convey my ſelfe through my Argument, and be the better conceived of you that are to heare me, I will divide that which I have to ſay into certain parts, which I will proſecute in order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I hold it neceſſary to conſider whether Cuſtom were due to the king by the Common-Law.</p>
            <p>Secondly, admitting it to bee due by the Common-Law, whether it were a ſumme cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, not to be increaſed at the kings pleaſure, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſuppoſing that by the Common-Law the king might, by way of impoſition,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157030:7"/> have increaſed his Cuſtom at his owne will, by his abſolute power, without aſſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether or no hee bee not bound to the contrary by Acts of Parliament; In the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of which part, I will conſider the ſtrength of every Act of Parliament hitherto vouched to this purpoſe, anſwering, as I goe, ſuch obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as have been made againſt thoſe Statutes by ſuch as have mainteined that the king is not bound by them. I will alſo add a Statute or two as yet not remembred by any. Laſtly, I will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover unto you the weakneſſe of ſuch Reaſons as have been made in maintenance of the Kings right to Impoſe; in the proſecuting of which parts I will (as occaſion is offered) give ſome anſwere to that which hath been laſt ſpoken; as knowing it to be expected at my hands.<note place="margin">By Sir <hi>Robert Hitcham.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then to conſider <hi>Whether there were by the Common-Law any duty belonging to the King upon Merchandize to be caried into or out of the kingdom, known by the name of Cuſtom.</hi> Though the mainteinance of Cuſtome to be due by the Common-Law be a point of ſuch conſequence to them that mainteined the Kings right to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as without the upholding of which their opinion (as I conceive) is not ſo much as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourably to be mainteined, and that to maintein the ſame it be not at all neceſſary to induce my concluſion; and although to admit it, it may ſeem perhaps no good policy of Argument, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:157030:8"/> rather a great diſadvantage to me to admit that, without which the contrary part cannot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their opinion, and which being admitted cannot make any thing for me; yet becauſe we are here not as Arguers at the Bar, but as Judges in a high-Court, and that all our ends tend to the diſcovery of the truth: I will therefore not only admit it, but will maintein it as well as I can.</p>
            <p>That Cuſtom is due by the Common-Law I collect,<note place="margin">That there was ever ſome Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome due by the Common Law.</note> firſt by the name thereof, for though at this day it bee (and ſo hath beene for more then 350 yeeres as I ſhall have occaſion more fully anon to open unto you) called in our law-Latin <hi>Cuſtuma,</hi> yet in ancient time it had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name here amongſt us (for I meane not to wander into forreign-learning) then <hi>Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> as may appeare by the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> cap. 30. <hi>Per rectas &amp; antiquas Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines</hi> (for I ſhall anon directly prove unto you that <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> in that place is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, a uſage, as hath been ſaid; but in that ſence which I, take it.) This name <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> in the ſame ſenſe is alſo found in many ancient Records brought into this houſe upon the late ſearch; That this name then <hi>Conſuetudo,</hi> which implies an approved continuance without a known beginning ſhould by the Common-Law be given to this Revenue more then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Revenue belonging to the King; nay, that this terme which is the common and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:157030:8"/> name to all common and approved uſages, of what nature or kinde ſoever ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to this dutie rather then to any other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the ancient uſages and Cuſtomes which the Common-Law imbraceth, cannot but denote the great antiquity thereof, and more then ſo, the allowance and approbation thereof by the Common-Law; for doubtleſſe, if, beſide the antiquity of this dutie, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law had not alſo alowed the reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, and in a manner the neceſſity of it, it would never have denoted it unto us by this name of excellency above all other Cuſtomes which require reaſonablenes as well as antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Therfore doubtleſſe this duty, thus favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is a Childe of the Common-Law; nay far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is of the very eſſence of a Cuſtome to have his only beginning by alowance of the Common-Law; for that which beginneth by private contract of partie, or by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; dependeth not wholly upon the alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Common-Law (by one of which three waies, all things conſiderable in Law, have their commencements) cannot bee called or bee a Cuſtome, in Name or Deede; moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſidering that this Cuſtome is not limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any one place within the Realme, wee ſhall ſo little neede to be curious in affirming it to bee due by the Common-Law, as wee may boldly pronounce it to be part of the Common-Law it ſelfe. Thus you ſee that the very name
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:157030:9"/> 
               <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> proves Cuſtome to bee a dutie by Common-Law: To this may bee added that <hi>Magna Charta</hi> cap. 30. which (Statute was made little more then 150 yeeres after the Conqueſt) termeth this not only <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> (which as I have ſaid, implies Antiquity beyond all remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of a beginning) but <hi>Antiqua Conſuetudo;</hi> not onely Cuſtome, but old and ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. And in compariſon to this old Cuſtome due at Common-Law, the Cuſtome upon Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Commodities, given or increaſed by act of Parliament, 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. not printed, was called <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va Conſuetudo:</hi> Before the making of which Statute of 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. you may further ſee, that Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome was due: For <hi>an.</hi> 52. <hi>H.</hi> 3. in the Statute of the Exchequer, printed, you may read, that the Collectors of the Cuſtome of Wools were to yeeld their accompt twice every yeere into the Exchequer. But that which moſt of all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me to beleeve that this duty was and is due by the Common-Law, is this; That in all Caſes where the Common-Law putteth the King to ſuſtaine Charge for the protection of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, it alwayes yeeldeth him out of the thing protected ſome gaine towards the maintenance of the Charge: As for the protection of Wards, Lunatiques, and Ideots, the profits of their Lands; For the maintenance of the Courts of Juſtice, it giveth him Fines for purchaſe of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall writs, and Fines <hi>pro licentia Concordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> which in ſuppoſition of Law are no other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:157030:9"/> than Fines paid for not proceeding according to the ſurety by pledges, put in upon purchaſe of the Originall; and for troubling without cauſe the Kings Juſtices, who are maintained in their places at the Kings charge: There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the like profits of Court given by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law to the King for the maintenance of his charge in the adminiſtring of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>This obſervation, which might be further proved by divers other inſtances in things of other nature, maketh me to think, that becauſe the Common-Law expecteth that the King ſhould protect Merchants in their Trades, by maintaining, repairing, and fortifying the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens at home; by clearing the Sea of Pirates and Enemies in their paſſage; and by maintaining Ambaſſadors abroad to treate with forreigne Princes upon all ſuch occaſions: That it alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him out of Merchandizes exported and imported, ſome profit for the ſuſtentation of this publique charge; otherwiſe were the Law very unreaſonable and unjuſt. So as to prove that by the Common-Law Cuſtome is due to the King, I ſhall need to ſay no more; eſpecially conſidering it hath not onely been yeelded to, but proved by thoſe which maintain a contrary Concluſion. I will therefore proceed to my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Conſideration: <hi>Whether that profit upon Merchandizes, which the Common-Law for theſe reſpects gave unto the King, were a duty cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, not to be increaſed or inhaunced at the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:157030:10"/> Kings will and pleaſure, without a common aſſent in Parliament? Or otherwiſe, Whether the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law hath left an abſolute power in the King, to demand in this caſe more or leſſe at his owne pleaſure, and to compell his Subjects to pay it?</hi> The reſolving of which queſtion will as I conceive, make an end of this controverſie between us; for what are theſe Impoſitions which wee complaine of, other than the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauncing of the Cuſtome by the Kings abſolute pleaſure?</p>
            <p>That this duty given by the Common-Law (as I have proved) unto the King,<note place="margin">That Cuſtome due by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, was a Sum certain.</note> was and is a duty certain, not to be enhaunced by the King at his owne pleaſure, without aſſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I hope I ſhall be able cleerly to prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you: In mainteinance of which, I will uſe ſome Arguments of direct proofe, and others of great preſumption and probability. And firſt, I lay this as a ground which will not be denyed me by any man; <hi>That the Common-Law of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>(as alſo all other wiſe Lawes in the World) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in certainty, and abandon incertainty, as the mother of all debate and confuſion, than which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more odious in Law:</hi> And therfore the rule is, <hi>Quod certum eſt retinendum eſt, quod in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certum eſt dimittendum;</hi> nay further, <hi>quod in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certum eſt nihil eſt:</hi> This is the cenſure of Law upon all the acts of men which fall under the judgment of the Law. If then the Law ſo judge of the acts of men, holding them for nought and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:157030:10"/> voyde that are incertaine; how much more then doth the Law require certainty in her own Acts, which are to binde all men: And if in any of the acts of Law certainty be to be ſpecially expected, moſt of all is it requiſite that bounds of limitation and certainty be ſet between the King and his poor Subject, between the mighty and the weak, between the Lion and the Lamb. And if in any Caſe between the King and his Subject more than other, this certainty be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, moſt of all it is requiſite in Caſes where the Common-Law giveth the King a perpetuall profit or revenue to be raiſed out of the intereſt and property of his poor Subjects eſtate, either in lands or goods. If in all other things the Law (as I have ſaid, and wherein I ſuppoſe you have yeelded to me) doe require certainty and limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and onely in this caſe where it is moſt requiſite, it hath omitted and neglected it, we muſt conclude the Law to be moſt unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, improvident, and contrary to it ſelfe; which to ſay, were to conclude it to be no Law. Out of theſe grounds I may then in my opinion ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with ſome confidence deduce and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this poſition;<note place="margin">That all the Revenue; which the Common Law giveth to the King out of the intereſt of the Subject are certain, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceable to a certainty by a legall courſe: and none left to the Kings pleaſure.</note> 
               <hi>That the Common-Law of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>giveth to the King, as to the head of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, no perpetuall revenue or matter of profit out of the intereſt or property of the Subject, but it either limiteth a certainty therein at the firſt, or otherwiſe hath ſo provided, that if it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine in it ſelfe, it is reduceable to a certainty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:157030:11"/> onely by a legal courſe, that is to ſay, either by Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, by Judges, or Jury; &amp; not by the Kings own abſolute will and pleaſure.</hi> Though this Poſition be grounded upon thoſe ſure foundations out of which I have (as you perceive) drawn it, and needs no farther proof: yet becauſe you ſhal ſee how plentiful the truth is in reaſons to maintain it ſelfe, I will further open unto you the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reaſons of this poſition, which are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Law requireth certainty in matter of profit,<note place="margin">The Reaſons why the Law requireth ſuch certainty in thoſe Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues.</note> between the King and the poor Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, becauſe to make any man Judge in his own caſe, eſpecially the mighty over the weake, and that in a point of profit to him that judgeth, were to leave a way open to oppreſſion and bondage.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe by reducing it to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, the King may know what certainty to expect; that ſo he may order his charge accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the Subject may know like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what he is to pay, that ſo he may know certainly what ſhall remaine to him as his own.</p>
            <p>Finally, that the King may not depend upon the good will of his Subject for his revenue, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law expecteth he ſhould beare the charge, but may know in certainty what to claime as due to him, and may accordingly compell the Subject to pay it; and that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may not be under the Kings abſolute pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to pay what the King pleaſeth, which may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:157030:11"/> perhaps extend to the whole value of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize.</p>
            <p>You ſee in generall, how the Law by requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring certainty in matter of profit between the King and the Subject, preventeth many miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheifes which would fall out if the Law were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; and therefore without more ſaying, I might here conclude, that Cuſtome being due by the Common-Law, was and is a ſum certain, not to be increaſed at the Kings pleaſure by way of Impoſition: but becauſe there are many other revenues due to the King by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law, as well as Cuſtome; if they all, or as many as we can call to minde, ſhall fall out to bee (as I have ſaid) ſummes certaine and not ſubject to bee increaſed at the kings will, this will bee a forcible Argument, that cuſtome is likewiſe certain and not to be inhannced at the kings pleaſure; for, this Argument drawne <hi>à ſimili</hi> is of great force, and the moſt uſuall of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other in debate of things doubtfull in Law. <hi>Quae Legibus deciſa non ſunt Index ex his quae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſa ſunt ſtatuet, &amp; de ſimilibus ad ſimilia proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat.</hi> May it pleaſe you to conſider in this reſpect other revenues which the Common-Law of this Land giveth the King;<note place="margin">Examples of Revenues gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-Law to the King, out of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Subject; that they are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</note> and according to the rule, to decide that which is in queſtion by the ſame rule and meaſure by which other things of the ſame nature have been decided and ordered. The Common-Law giveth the King a Fine for the purchaſe of an original writ;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:157030:12"/> Is it certaine? it is, and ever hath been; if the debt or damages demanded amount to above forty pounds, the Fine is, and ever hath been ſixe ſhil. eight pence, and no more: if to a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, then ten ſhillings, and no more: May the King increaſe this Fine at his pleaſure? there is no man that will ſay he may. There is a Fine due by the Common-Law, <hi>pro Licentia concordandi;</hi> is it not certainly known, and ſo hath alwayes been, to be the tenth part of the Land compriſed in the writ of Covenant? And is not alſo the Poſt-Fine thereupon due certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known to be once and a halfe as much more as the Fine <hi>pro licentia concordandi,</hi> or Pre-Fine? As for example, when the Pre-fine is ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the Poſt-fine to be fifteen ſhillings: and can the King demand any more of the Subject? So likewiſe, when in a writ of Right, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandant alleadging the ſeiſin of his Anceſtor, will not be compelled to prove the ſeiſin allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, is he not to tender to the King a ſumme cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of a demy-mark, to have this benefit? was it ever more or leſſe? or can it now be more if the King would? theſe, amongſt many others, are duties belonging to the King by the Common Law from the Subject, for the maintaina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his Charge in the adminiſtration of Juſtice, which the Civilians call <hi>Vectigal Judiciarium.</hi> There are alſo in divers other Caſes duties certain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the King by the Common-Law: As for example; the reliefe for an Earledome is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:157030:12"/> knowne to be a hundred pounds; for a Barony a hundred markes; for a Knights fee a hundred ſhillings: all which in the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta, cap.</hi> are called old and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient duties: this is <hi>Vectigal Patrimoniale;</hi> of which ſort I could produce many others, all which have like certainty. Nay, there is one duty well known to us all, which the Common-Law giveth to the King; and is in his nature a Cuſtome (our very caſe) in which the King is bound to a certainty which he cannot exceed; and that is <hi>Priſage,</hi> a duty given by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law to the King, upon every ſhiploading of Wine brought into the kingdom by Engliſh Merchants; and is one Tun of Wine before the Maſt, and another behinde. I am unwilling to trouble you with any more particulars of this kinde: but let any man ſhew me one particular to the contrary, and I will then yeeld, that my poſition being falſe in one, may be in more: But till my poſition hath been in this point infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, this generall concordance of the Law in all theſe particulars, is argument enough for me, without having aleadged other reaſons, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that Cuſtome being as all theſe are, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue due to the King by the Common-Law, ariſing out of the Property and intereſt of the Subject, is (as all theſe are) limited and bounded by the Common-Law to a certainty, which the King hath not power to increaſe: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eadem Ratio, eadem Lex.</hi> It may perhaps be here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:157030:13"/> that the Ayd paid to the King upon the Knighting of his eldeſt Sonne, or marriage of his eldeſt Daughter, was by the Common-Law uncertaine; and that the King did take more or leſſe at his pleaſure, untill he was bound to the contrary by Statute. To this I make divers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers: Though it were indeed a ſumme uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, yet the Common-Law did in ſome ſort give it a limitation; for it is by a ſpeciall name called <hi>Reaſonable Ayd:</hi> So as if the ſumme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded doe exceed Reaſon, it became from a <hi>Reaſonable Ayd</hi> an unjuſt exaction. Beſides, this revenue was a thing happening very rarely, and therefore the certainty thereof not ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by the Law: and yet it is to be obſerved how the frame of this Common-wealth could not long indure incertainty even in this caſuall Revenue; but it was reduced to a certainty of twenty ſhillings upon a Knights fee, and 20<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. upon every twenty pounds Soccageland, by the Stat. of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 35.3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. If in this caſuall Revenue they were ſo carefull to be at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, to avoid unreaſonable exactions (as the words of the Statute are) how much more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full would they have been, for the ſame cauſe to have reduced the great and annuall Revenue of the Cuſtome to a certainty, if they had not thought it to have been certaine by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law, or limited by Statute-Law before that time made? But (Sir) that which I rely upon for anſwer to this objection, is this: Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:157030:13"/> Ayd was and is by the Common-Law due as well to meane Lords as to the King: But meane Lords were not limited to a certainty, otherwiſe than in generall, that it muſt be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as I have ſaid; therefore to limit the King any further, was no reaſon: And this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may be given for all uncertaine Revenues belonging to the King, the like of which mean Lords have of their Tenants; for the incertainty of which there may alſo be given eſpeciall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe theſe duties firſt began by ſpeciall contract and agreement between the Lord and the Tenant, and not directly by operation of the Common Law, and ſo were certain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain as they did at firſt agree: and therefore you may be pleaſed to remember, how in laying my poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was wary to ſay, <hi>That ſuch revenues as are due to the King as to the head of the Common wealth</hi> (by which I purpoſely excluded ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues as are common to him with other mean Lords) <hi>are alwayes certaine.</hi> I am now accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to promiſe, and in maintenance of a ſecond part of my poſition, to ſhew you, <hi>That where the Common-Law giveth the King a Revenue not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine at the firſt, that is alwayes reduceable to a certainty by a legal courſe, as by act of Parliament, Judges, or Jury, and not at the Kings pleaſure.</hi> Every man that by his tenure is bound to ſerve the King in his warres, and faileth, is to pay according to the quantity of his Tenure, a fine by the name of Eſcuage; this cannot be aſſeſſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:157030:14"/> but in Parliament: Upon forfeitures for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or otherwiſe, to the King; though it be a kinde of a certainty that the Law giveth, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him all the eſtate of the party convict, both in goods and Lands, or in goods onely, as the caſe is; yet for reducing it to a more expreſſe certainty, the Law requireth that it be found by Office. <hi>Wayfe, Stray, Wreck, Treaſure-Trove,</hi> and ſuch like, are no leſſe certaine; for the King hath the things themſelves in kinde. Fines for miſdemeanors are alwayes aſſeſſed by the Judges, Amercements in all caſes are to be afferred by the Country, and not to be aſſeſſed by the King, though the forme of the Judgement be, <hi>Et ſit in miſecordia Domini Regis,</hi> in the Kings mercy <hi>pro contemptu predict.</hi> Nay, though for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an offence it be by Statute-Law ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that an offendor ſhall make Fine and Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome at the Kings pleaſure, the Law even in this caſe (which is as ſtrong a caſe as may be) will not leave the aſſeſſing of the Fine to the Kings pleaſure, to be by him rated privately in his Chamber; but it muſt be ſolemnly and legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done in an open Court of Juſtice by the Judges, who in all other caſes are to judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and his people, where the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or property of the Subject, or any charge or burden upon them doth come in queſtion, as may be proved by the booke of 2 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>fo.</hi> 11. Inſomuch that I am of opinion, that if a Statute were made, that the King might raiſe the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:157030:14"/> at his pleaſure, yet might it not be done as now it is, by the Kings abſolute power, but by ſome other legall courſe, of which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law doth take notice; as in the caſe of the Fine and Ranſome: much leſſe then will the Common-Law permit, that it ſhould depend upon the Kings abſolute pleaſure, there being no ſuch Statute in the caſe.</p>
            <p>You have heard out of what grounds I firſt deduced this my poſition, <hi>That the Law requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth certainty in matter of profit between the King and his people.</hi> You have heard likewiſe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reaſons of that poſition: you have alſo heard what proofe I have made by particular ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of like nature to this in queſtion; and how I have applyed them to the point: And ſo lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Judgement of the whole to your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, who can beſt diſcerne whether the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument be of weight, I proceed to my ſecond Reaſon, which is drawne from <hi>the policy and frame of this Common-wealth, and the providence of the Common-Law: The which, as it requires at the Subjects hands loyalty and obedience to their Soveraigne; ſo doth it likewiſe require at the hands of the Soveraigne, protection and defence of the Subject againſt all wrongs and injuries whatſoever offered either by one Subject to another, or by the Common Enemy to them all, or any of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Protection, the Law conſidereth, cannot be without a great charge to the King;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:157030:15"/> And becauſe, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>No man goeth to warre upon his owne charge;</hi> the Common-Law therefore hath not onely given the King great Prerogatives and favours touching his own pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, more (I beleeve) than any other Prince in the world hath; but alſo hath, for the ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his great and neceſſary expences in the protection of his Subjects, given him out of the intereſt and property of the Subject an ample, and very honorable revenue in very many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſes, ſome of which I will call to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
            <p>He receiveth out of the Subjects purſe for wardſhips and the dependances thereupon, as we have of late accounted, about forty five thouſand pounds by the yeare. This is a Revenue which no other King of the world hath: And as it appeares by the Statute of 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>It ought to be imployed in mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the warres;</hi> and ſo doubtleſſe was the firſt inſtitution of the Common-Law: For the Lord hath the profit of the Wards lands to no other end, than to maintain a man in the warre during the infancy of him who otherwiſe ſhould ſerve in perſon.</p>
            <p>He hath likewiſe all forfeitures upon Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Outlawry, and upon penall Lawes, Fines and Amerciaments, Profits of Courts, Treaſure-Trove, Priſage, Butlerage, Wreck, and ſo many more, as the very enumeration of the particulars would take up long
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:157030:15"/> time. To what other end hath the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law thus provided for the maintenance of the Kings charge, by all theſe wayes and meanes of raiſing profit out of the Intereſt and property of the Subjects eſtate in lands and goods, but onely to this end, That after theſe duties paid, the poore Subject might hold and enjoy the reſt of his eſtate to his owne uſe, free and cleare from all other burdens whatſoever? To what end hath the Law given a part to the King, and left the reſt to the Subject, if that which is left be alſo at the Kings will, to make his profit thereof as he pleaſeth? To give a ſmall portion to him that may at his pleaſure take more, or all, is a vain and an idle act; which ſhal never be imputed to a wiſe Law. But it may be objected that as the revenues are ordinary,<note place="margin">Anſwere to an objection, that the King may lay Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in times of extraordinary occaſions.</note> ſo are they by the Law provided onely for the ſuſteyning of the kings ordinary charge; and that if the Law have not taken further conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and limmitted ſome certain courſe, how upon ſudden and extraordinary occaſions the kings charge may bee ſuſteined, that there is yet no reaſon ſhewed to the contrary, why the king may not upon ſuch occaſion take ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary courſe for the rayſing of money, as by the laying of Impoſitions upon Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, or by a tax within the Realme, rather then the Common wealth for want thereof, ſhould periſh or be indangered.<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Robert Hitcham.</hi>
               </note> And hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the knight that laſt ſpake, it was held that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:157030:16"/> 
               <hi>upon occaſion of a ſudden and unexpected war, the King may not only lay impoſitions, but levy a tax within the Realme, without aſſent of Parliament,</hi> which poſition in my opinion is very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; for to admit this were by conſequence to bring us into bondage. You ſay that upon occaſion of ſuddaine warre the king may levy a Tax; who ſhall be Judge between the king and his people of the occaſion? can it be tryed by any Legall courſe in our Law? it cannot: if then, the king himſelfe muſt be the ſole Judge in this caſe, will it not follow that the king may levie a taxe at his owne pleaſure, ſeeing his pleaſure cannot be bounded by Law? You ſee into what a miſchiefe the admittance of one er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror hath drawne you. But for a full anſwer to the objection, I ſay, that the providence of the Common-Law is ſuch, and ſo excellent, as that for the defraying of the kings charge upon any occaſions of a ſuddain warre, it hath, over and above all the ordinary Revenues which it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the king (which in the time of warre can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not indeed but fall ſhort) made an excellent proviſion; for (Sir) <hi>The warre muſt needs be either offenſive or defenſive: Offenſive,</hi> muſt either be upon ſome Nation beyond the Seas, or againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> or <hi>Welſh,</hi> or other borderers within the Iland: If it be an <hi>offenſive</hi> warre upon ſome Nation beyond the Seas, it cannot be a ſudden Accident, for it is the kings own act; and he may, and 'tis fitting he ſhould take deliberation;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:157030:16"/> and if it be a juſt and neceſſary warre, he may crave, and eaſily obtaine aſſiſtance of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by grant of Ayd in Parliament: <hi>If an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive warre upon ſome of his neighbors within the Continent of this Iland,</hi> as the <hi>Scots,</hi> or the <hi>Welſh,</hi> which alſo cannot be ſudden or unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the king, being his own act; you know how politikely the kings of this Realme have provided, by reſerving Tenures, by which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Subjects are bound to ſerve them in thoſe warres in perſon, at their owne charge: Only a <hi>Defenſive warre,</hi> by invaſion of forreign enemies, may be ſodain: in which caſe the Law hath not left the king to warre upon his owne expence, or to rely upon his ordinary Revenue, but hath notably provided, That every Subject within the Land, high and low, whether he hold of the king or not, in caſe of forreign In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion may be compelled at his own charge to ſerve the king in perſon, as it appeares by the opinion of Juſtice <hi>Thirming,</hi> in 7 <hi>H.</hi> 4. The reaſon of which, in my opinion, was to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, than that the king might have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever for the raiſing of money upon his Subjects at his owne pleaſure, without their common aſſent in Parliament. I doe then conclude this Argument, that ſeeing the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law for maintenance of the Kings ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary charge, hath given him ſuch an ample Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue out of the intereſt and property of the Subject, and provided alſo for ſodaine occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:157030:17"/> that in ſo doing it hath ſecluded and ſecured the reſt of the Subjects eſtate from the Kings power and pleaſure; and conſequently, that the King hath not power upon any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at his pleaſure to charge the eſtate of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects by Impoſitions, Tallages, or Taxes (for I hold them all in one degree) or any other bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den whatſoever, without the Subjects free and voluntary aſſent, and that in Parliament: If it were otherwiſe, you ſee how it were to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſſolution and deſtruction of that politike frame &amp; conſtitution of this Common-wealth, which I have opened unto you; and of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wiſe providence of the Common-Law, for the preſerving of property, and the avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of oppreſſion. Theſe two Arguments u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by me, that of <hi>Certainty,</hi> and this of <hi>the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made by the Common-Law,</hi> are in my poor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, Arguments of direct proofe, that the King cannot Impoſe. I will now, according to my diviſion, urge an Argument or two of Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and preſumption; the rather, becauſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of this nature have been much enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by thoſe who have maintained the contrary opinion,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Francis Bacon.</hi>
               </note> (eſpecially by Mr. Solicitor:) I call them Arguments of inference, and yet in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, thoſe which I ſhall urge are alſo of good proofe; ſuch as they are, you ſhall judge of them. <hi>They are drawne either from the actions or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearances of the Kings of this Realme, or, from the actions and forbearances of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:157030:17"/>
            <p> Firſt, in the actions and forbearances of the Kings,<note place="margin">Arguments drawne from the actions of the Kings, that they have no power to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> I obſerve, that all the Kings of this Realm ſince <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. have ſought and obteined an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Cuſtome, more or leſſe, by the name of Subſidie, of the gift of their Subjects in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: Nay, ſome of them, and thoſe not the weakeſt in Spirit, or power, but the moſt cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and potent in that whole ranke, even that mighty and victorious Prince, King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. being to undertake a juſt and honorable warre, than which there could not happen a better or juſter occaſion to have made uſe of his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of Impoſing, did nevertheleſſe at that time ſtoope ſo low in this point, that he did in full aſſembly of the three States, pray his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to grant him a Reliefe in this kinde for the maintenance of his warre, and that to endure but for a ſhort time; and further, was well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſuffer his prayer in that behalfe to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of Record to the memory of all poſterity: And the ſucceeding Kings have alſo ſuffered the ſame to be printed, as may appeare by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Statutes at large, <hi>An.</hi> 14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. Is it likely, that if any or all theſe Kings had thought they had had in them any lawfull power by juſt Prerogative to have laid Impoſitions at their pleaſure, that they would not rather have made uſe of that, than have taken this courſe by act of Parliament, ſo full of delay, ſo prejudiciall to their Right, ſo ſubject to the pleaſure of their people, who never undergoe Burdens but with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:157030:18"/> murmuring and much unwillingnes: Can there be any thing more hatefull to the high Spirit of a King, than to ſubject himſelfe to the pleaſure of his people, eſpecially for matter of Reliefe, and that by way of Prayer, having lawfull pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his hands to relieve himſelfe without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beholding to them?</p>
            <p>If perhaps the Kings themſelves were igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this great Prerogative, which cannot be imagined; had they not alwaies about them wiſe Counſellors to aſſiſt them, and ſuch as for the procuring of favor to themſelves would not have failed to have put them in minde of it? Nay, if they had known any ſuch lawfull Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, had they not been bound in conſcience ſo to have done? What an overſight was it of King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and all his Counſell, ſo much to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice his right in ſo beneficiall a Prerogative; as to ſuffer him upon Record, and that in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to pray for that which he might have taken out of his abſolute power? Can there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt be a more direct diſclaiming in the Right, (to compare great things with leſſe) if the Lord by matter of Record claime any thing of his villaine, it is a diſclaimer of the villenage.</p>
            <p>The Kings of England have other noble and high Prerogatives; I will only name two of them, The making of warre and peace, and the raiſing and abaſing of Coyne at their pleaſure: Did they ever crave the aſſent of their Subjects in Parliament to make a warre? Their advice
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:157030:18"/> indeed they have ſometimes ſought, and their ayd for treaſure to maintaine it. The Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of raiſing and abaſing the value of money hath been oftentimes put in practiſe by them, and ſometimes ſtrayned to ſuch a height, that the King might well ſuppoſe the Subjects could not but be much diſcontent therewith: And yet never any King of this Realme did it by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament, which perhaps ſome one milde King among ſo many would have done, and it may be, would alſo have prayed his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to yield thereto, only to avoid the grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the people, if the ſeeking of aſſent in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had not been thought to have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall to the abſolute power of their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: and yet, as for ſome of theſe Kings, it may be ſuppoſed, they made little conſcience to preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice a Succeſſor in one point, that made no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple totally to depoſe a Predeceſſor from his Throne, and all his Regalities, and to uſurp it to themſelves.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed to my next Argument of Inference drawn from the actions of our Kings. Some of the Kings of England, as namely; <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the 2.</note> in the yeere of his Reigne, and <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. in the 1. and 24. yeere of his Reigne, as may appeare by the Records here amongſt us, were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to accept an increaſe of their Cuſtome <hi>by way of Loane</hi> from the Merchants, and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binde themſelves to repay it againe. Would any wiſe man in the world, that thought he had
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:157030:19"/> but a colour of Right, ſo much prejudice his himſelf, as to borrow that which he might take without leave, and binde himſelfe to repay it. If a poore man perhaps through feare might be enforced ſo farre to yeeld to a mighty adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet that a powerfull man ſhould ſtoope ſo low to one much weaker than he; nay, that a King, in a point of ſuch conſequence, ſhould ſo farre diſcend from his Greatneſſe, as to borrow of his poore Subject that which without being beholding to him he might obtein as his Right; and binde himſelfe to repay it againe: I ſay, it cannot with any reaſon be imagined; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all it muſt be concluded, that a king that ſhall ſo doe, doth not thinke that he hath ſo much as colour of Right to impoſe.</p>
            <p>I will not much preſſe or enforce the actions of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. who (I confeſſe) was but a weake Prince;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the 3.</note> But as for his Sonne and ſucceſſor, <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. there was not (as I have ſaid) a ſtouter, a wiſer, a more noble and couragious Prince than he, and none more carefull to preſerve the Rights of his Prerogative, as may evidently appeare by all his anſwers in Parliament, on any complaint of the Subject. Beſides, never had king of this Realme more occaſion than he to ſtraine this Prerogative of impoſing to the utmoſt: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his exceſſive expence in the warres of France and Scotland, he had alſo a continuall charge of many expenſive children, his wife Queene <hi>Philip</hi> had alſo for her maintenance a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:157030:19"/> large allowance out of his Revenue; but the dowry of Queen <hi>Iſabell</hi> his mother (who lived till about the 27. yeere of his Reigne) was ſo great, as it is reported by ſome writers, that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more than the third part of the certaine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of the kingdome was left to him: In ſo much, as through theſe occaſions of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary expence, and the diminution of his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, he was driven to ſuch neceſſity, as his Queen in the <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> yeere of his Reigne, was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to pawne her Crowne and Jewels to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure money for him, as may appeare by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of that yeere in the Office of the Clerke of the Pels. Nay, the king himſelfe in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, was oftentimes driven to lay his Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els to pawne for money: And in <hi>An.</hi> 17. did alſo pledge his Crown for 4000. pound, to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Merchants of <hi>Florence,</hi> as by the Records of that yeere, in the Office of the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Remembrancer in the Exchequer, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. By this you may ſee, that this powerfull king wanted not urgent and juſt occaſion (if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſion may be juſt) to have put in practiſe his abſolute power of Impoſing; and yet, as you ſee, it appeares of Record, that in the midſt of his great wants he tooke an increaſe of Cuſtome <hi>by way of Loane,</hi> and bound himſelfe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay it.</p>
            <p>It may be here objected, that he did lay Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
            <p>What Impoſitions they were, and how to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:157030:20"/> be compared with the Impoſitions now in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, I purpoſe to tell you, when I come to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r objections, which I have referred to the end of my ſpeech: In the meane time I will goe on with my courſe, and urge one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more, drawne from the actions of our kings, touching the increaſe of Cuſtome.</p>
            <p>A man would thinke, that the taking of the increaſe of Cuſtome by all the kings, both one and other, with the aſſent of their Subjects in Parliament, and ſometimes by way of Prayer and Intreaty, for a ſhort time; nay, the taking of it by way of Loane, and binding themſelves to repay it; and that to have been done by the moſt powerfull kings, in their greateſt neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were Argument enough that they did not beleeve they might juſtly claime it as their right by their abſolute power.</p>
            <p>And yet is not this all: For, ſome of them, by name, <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the 1.</note> did not onely take it by aſſent in Parliament, or <hi>by way of Loane,</hi> but (as one that buyes for his mony in the Market) did give for it a reall and valuable conſideration, and that to Merchant-ſtrangers, of whom there was more colour to demand it as a duty, than of his naturall Subjects. In proofe of which I produce <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> made <hi>Anno</hi> 31. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is recited, that in lieu of certaine liberties and immunities granted by the king to the Merchant-ſtrangers, as alſo for the releaſe of Priſage, they granted to the king an increaſe of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:157030:20"/> Cuſtom. What were all the ſpecial liberties that were granted them, I know not, nor whether they continue; but ſure I am, that by vertue of that Grant they are at this day free of Priſage, paying onely 2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. upon a Tun of Wine, by the name of Butlerage, which they granted by the ſame Charter: whereas Engliſh-men pay Priſage <hi>in ſpecie, viz.</hi> One Tun before the Maſt, and one Tun behinde.</p>
            <p>And it is very worthy the obſervation, how the ſame King, <hi>E.</hi> 1. in the ſame yeer of his reign did command his Cuſtomers throughout <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> That whereas certain Engliſh Merchants were, as he was informed, of their own accords willing to pay him the like increaſe of Cuſtome which the Merchant ſtrangers had granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, ſo as they might enjoy the like liberties and benefits; that nevertheleſſe they ſhould not compell ſuch Engliſh Merchants, againſt their wils, to pay it: the words are worth the hearing: <hi>Cum quidam Mercatores de regno &amp; poteſtate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, ut ipſi dictis libertat.</hi> (having before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Charta Mercatoria) uti &amp; gandere, &amp; de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis naſtris quieti eſſe poſſint; praeſtationes &amp; Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumas hujuſmodi, de bonis &amp; mercandizis ſuis nobis dare &amp; ſolvere velint; ut accepimus, aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navimus vos ad praeſtationes &amp; Cuſtumas prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictas, de his qui praeſtationes &amp; Cuſtumasillas gratanter &amp; abſque cohercione ſolvere volnerint, colligendum, &amp; ad opus noſtrum recipiendum; ita tamen quod aliquem Mercatorem de dicto Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:157030:21"/> noſtro ad hujuſmodi praeſtationes &amp; Cuſtumas nobis invite ſolvendum nullatenus diſtringatis.</hi> What ſtronger inference can there almoſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be againſt the Kings abſolute power of Impoſing, than this: that he was contented, and ſo ſpecified to all his Officers of the Ports, That if the Merchants did of their own accords pay more than their ancient Cuſtomes, they ſhould have conſideration for it; But if they themſelves were not willing to pay more, then they ſhould not be compelled thereunto.</p>
            <p>One other obſervation I draw from the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the kings touching the increaſe of their cuſtome, which is this, that thoſe kings which did lay Impoſitions (which as I will ſhew you by and by, was very rarely) though it were never but in time of great neceſſity, and but to indure for a ſhort time; yet they alwayes did it, not with the advice alone of the Merchants, as at this day, but <hi>the Merchants did alwaies ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly grant an increaſe of Cuſtome;</hi> and the kings were alwayes wary, for the better juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of their actions to the people, in their Commiſſions for collecting of Cuſtome, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite not onely the great neceſſity which moved them to take an increaſe of Cuſtome, but alſo <hi>the grant of the Merchants,</hi> as may appeare by the Records, of which we have the copies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; I dare confidently ſay, there is not above one or two at the moſt that are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if the Impoſitions be of that nature which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:157030:21"/> theſe are of which we complaine; And yet theſe Impoſitions alſo, by the <hi>grant of Merchants,</hi> though raiſed upon never ſo great a neceſſitie of State, and to indure but for a ſhort time, were always complained of by the Commons, when they met in Parliament, as may appeare amongſt other Records, by the Parliament Roll of 27. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>No.</hi> 27. where in a Petition of the Commons, exhibited to the King in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are theſe words, <hi>Les Commons monſtrent coment que les Marchants dyent grant per eux ſans aſſent de Parliament, un ſubſidie de</hi> XL<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. <hi>de ſacc. de Layn, outre le droiturel male tout de demy marke. Et prion que ſoit amend a reſt Parliament. Car eſt encounter reaſon, que le Comialtie de lour biens ſoient per Marchants charges;</hi> Which I Engliſh thus, <hi>The Commons ſhew how the Merchants have granted by themſelves, wihout aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Subſidie of</hi> 40<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. <hi>upon a ſack of Wooll, over and above the rightfull cuſtome of halfe a Marke, and pray that it may be redreſſed at this Parliament; for it is againſt reaſon that the Comminalty ſhould be charged in their goods by Merchants:</hi> with this agreeth the printed Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. in the Statutes at large, where you ſhall finde an expreſſe Proviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rayſing of Impoſitions upon Woolls, <hi>by grant of Merchants,</hi> In which Petition I doe obſerve, that the Parliament in thoſe dayes did diſtinguiſh, even as we now doe, between Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions laid by act of Parliament, and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:157030:22"/> laid only by the grant of Merchants, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that Impoſitions laid by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are onely lawfull, and condemning all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as unlawfull, for otherwiſe why ſhould they tearme the demy-Marke, which was laid by Act of Parliament. 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>(Droiturel male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tout)</hi> a lawfull Impoſition: but with relation to the unlawfulneſſe of theſe Impoſitions gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Merchants, which they then did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of; Beſides, I obſerve that they ſay, That it is againſt reaſon, that Merchants ſhould by their grant, <hi>without aſſent in Parliament,</hi> charge the whole Commonaltie, by which it plainly appears, that they complained not ſo much of the exceſſe or greatneſſe of the Impoſitions, as of the unlawfull manner of the raiſing of it by grant of merchants, <hi>without aſſent in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto I have, according to my diviſion, drawne Arguments from that which our Kings have done, and put in practiſe for the increaſe of their Cuſtome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will now make ſome obſervations of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arguments drawn from the forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our Kings, to lay Impoſitions not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> 
               <hi>to put this pretended power in practiſe, conſidering the ſeverall occaſions of the times, which I will proſecute in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt therefore in generall, I obſerve, that from the Conqueſt, untill the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> being no leſſe then 480. yeeres ſpace, (whatſoever the occaſions were) whatſoever the diſpoſition of the Kings were, yet in the practiſe of this pretended Prerogative of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:157030:22"/> Impoſing the Kings have been ſo ſparing, as notwithſtanding, this curious ſearch, that hath been made (wherein I ſuppoſe nothing that might make for the cleering of the Queſtion, hath eſcaped us) it cannot be found or proved by matter of Record, that ſix Impoſitions (ſuch as we now complaine of) were laid by all thoſe Kings (who were in number 22. And thoſe ſixe (if they were ſo many) though they were unlawfull, yet were they in ſome ſort to be born withall. Firſt, by reaſon they were very mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; Secondly, that they were laid in the times of great and apparant neceſſitie, and that they were to endure but for a yeer or two; For none of them, except onely that upon Wine, laid 16. <hi>E.</hi> 1. laſted longer. They were (I ſay) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their unlawfulneſſe) yet in theſe other reſpects, ſo farre to be borne withall, as if the impoſitions which are now laid, had been ſo qualified, we ſhould I ſuppoſe, never have complained of them; and yet not one of theſe few impoſitions laid in former times, but was complained of, and upon complaint taken away, as may appear by the Records here amongſt us: How much more reaſon is there then, that we ſhould expect the like Juſtice now? conſidering that not one Merchandiſe alone, as then, but very neere all the ſorts and ſeverall kindes of Merchandiſes that are, are charged; that not a moderate and eaſy charge is laid upon them, but ſuch, as though we ſhould confeſſe his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:157030:23"/> abſolut power, to lay what he liſt, yet we had juſt cauſe to complain of the exceſſiveneſſe of the Burden: For firſt, the rates of Merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for the Subſidies of Poundage and Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, are extreamly rayſed (a thing alſo though lawfull, yet hath been rarely put in practiſe) then comes the Impoſt upon the back of that, and is as much as the Subſidie it ſelfe is; in ſome few Merchandiſes, 'tis true, the Impoſt is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps leſſe then the Subſidy, but 'tis as true, that in divers others, the Impoſt is farre more. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, theſe Impoſitions were not laid in the time of warre, but even then when we were at peace with all the world, except perhaps there were ſome ſparks of Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> then not fully quenched. Laſtly theſe Impoſitions are not (as thoſe in former time were) limited to endure for a yeere or two, but are to come to his Majeſtie, his Heires and Succeſſors for ever, as may appeare by his Majeſties Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in print, prefixed before the new book of Rates. So as if thoſe few Impoſitions laid in former times, had been lawfull, yet can they not by any means be a warrant or preſident for our preſent Impoſitions, differing ſo far from them in all theſe points of conſequence. But if even thoſe few, ſo quallified as they were, were complained of and taken away, what ſhall we then ſay of ours, ſo farre exceeding them in all the degrees of Irregularitie; Beſides, if ſo few Preſidents, as five or ſix in ſo many yeers ſpace,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:157030:23"/> and thoſe in times of ſo great neceſſitie, without any expreſſe Judgment in Law; or good autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in approbation of them, but accompanied with as many complaints againſt them, be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument enough to prove the lawfulneſſe of the act, I dare undertake, that as well taxes within the land, as Impoſitions upon Merchandizes may be proved to be lawfull: But to alledge the acts of kings, in rayſing a profit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon their Subjects, to prove thereby their right, is of all other arguments that are, the weakeſt, and ſo I leave it, and call to minde, that when I told you, it could not be proved by the Records amongſt us, that from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, there had been any more then ſixe Impoſitions laid; I did in that number, limit my ſelfe to ſuch Impoſitions as thoſe are which we now complain of, for I muſt confeſſe, that in that ſpace, many more Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions were laid, but they were of a farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nature from ours, differing I ſay, not only in thoſe circumſtances, by which I did even now compare the Impoſitions of theſe times to thoſe five or ſix of former ages, but in very eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and propertie, inſomuch as they may not properly be called Impoſitions, and yet the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent practiſe of them hath been objected and relyed upon, as ſo many Preſidents, to prove the lawfulneſſe of the Impoſitions now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned of: It behoveth me therefore, that in maintenance of my aſſertion, that ſo few Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:157030:24"/> have been laid, as I have affirmed, that I open unto you the difference betweene the one and the other, which being done, your ſelves will eaſily judge that the greater part make nothing towards the defence of theſe preſent Impoſitions; For theſe Impoſitions which now are in queſtion, are no other then an increaſe of Cuſtome, at the Kings pleaſure, and commanded by him to be taken, the paſſage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free and open to all men. Thoſe other which make ſuch a great ſhew in number, and are produced as ſo many Preſidents in mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of theſe, are no other then ſo many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations or Licences for money, to paſſe with Merchandizes prohibited by Act of Parliament to be exported, as will evidently appeare by comparing the times, and examining the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. I will therefore in this place, as ſhortly as I can, runne over thoſe Preſidents that have been, or may be alledged by the contrary part, out of thoſe Records which are here amongſt us, and leave it to your judgement, whether I maintaine my aſſertion, or be not rather better then my word for the number.</p>
            <p>The firſt Impoſition by them alledged,<note place="margin">Urged by <hi>Flem. Clark. Doderig.</hi>
               </note> is that of 16. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. which as it appears by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, was 4. ſhillings upon a Tun of Wine. This indeed, for ought I know to the contrary, was a meere Impoſition, ſuch as are now in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; and yet if I did deny it, and ſay that it was layd by aſſent of Parliament, I know not how
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:157030:24"/> the contrary could be proved, for though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the words of the Record are (<hi>Cum Rex precipiſſet, ut de ſingulis doliis vini caperentur</hi> 4. <hi>ſolidi</hi>) it follows not that it was laid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only by the kings commandment, for we ſee that even ſome Acts of Parliament, in thoſe auncient times, though they were made by the full aſſent of all the three Eſtates, yet they have theſe words in their preambles, <hi>(Rex precepit: Rex vult.)</hi> But as for Recitalls of Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by the King, in his Commiſſions, and otherwiſe, it was in thoſe times uſuall to ſay, <hi>(Cum nuper ordinaverimus)</hi> and therefore not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Recitall be <hi>(Cum nuper Rex precipiſſet)</hi> it is no cleere proof, that therefore it was done onely by the Kings Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nevertheleſſe I will, I ſay, admit this to be a meere Impoſition, and to be one of the number, and indeed, as this is the firſt they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, ſo is it their beſt, only this (amongſt all the reſt) is not limited to indure for a time certain: but give me leave (I beſeech you) to open unto you, with what circumſtances this Impoſition was accompanied, and what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of it, and then I will leave you to judge (who beſt are able) how far the preſent Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions may be juſtifyed by this; The firſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance to be obſerved in this Impoſition, is that it was laid immediately after the warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Wales</hi> was ended, and at the time, when for the ſelling of the Eſtate of <hi>Gaſcoigne,</hi> the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:157030:25"/> king himſelf was in perſon enforced to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a voyage thither, as may appeare by our Hiſtories of thoſe times, which alſo may bee collected by the very words of the record which are theſe, <hi>Cum Rex ante ultimum Receſſum ſuum ab Anglia precepiſset, &amp;c.</hi> That as theſe times were troubleſome, they were alſo very chargeable to the king, and did put him to try all meanes for the levying of money, I ſhall not need to urge it, it cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>One other circumſtance is this, that this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition laid in this time of great neceſſity was not, as now, upon all Merchandizes, nor ſo much as in generall upon one kinde of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, comming from all the parts of the world, but onely upon ſuch wines as were brought hither from two Towns in <hi>Gaſcoigne, Bergerac.</hi> and <hi>St. Emilians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">16. E. 1.22. E. 1. in Scacario.</note> as may appear by the Records, and it is probable that theſe Towns were then in revolt, &amp; that the ſooner to reduce them to obedience, the King laid this burden upon their commodities, thereby to hinder the vent of them.</p>
            <p>Another circumſtance is this, that though that this Impoſition were indeed laid without limitation of any time, as touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance thereof, yet within ſix years follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> 5. <hi>Decemb. a.</hi> 22. upon complaint of the Merchants the king releaſed two ſhillings of the foure ſhillings, as may appear by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:157030:25"/> of 22 <hi>E.</hi> 1. with which the Merchants not holding themſelves contented, the very ſame yeare within eight or nine months follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> 23. <hi>Juliian.</hi> 22. the whole Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was releaſed, as may appeare by a recitall in the accompt of one <hi>William Randall</hi> receiver of the Impoſt money entred, <hi>an.</hi> 26 <hi>E.</hi> 1. And within three years after the releaſe, <hi>viz, an.</hi> 25. there followed an act of Parliament againſt all Impoſitions in generall, as when I come to ſhew you what Statutes there are, in the point, I ſhall I hope cleerly prove unto you; In the meane time I will proceed to examine the reſt.</p>
            <p>The next preſident urged is an impoſition of 40. ſhillings upon a ſack of wooll laid by <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>an.</hi> 21. For the proofe of which, a record of the Exchequer of that year hath been vouched. I muſt confeſſe I have not ſeen that Record, but by another Record of the ſame Court, <hi>an.</hi> 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. it is evident that the ſaid Impoſition was not raiſed by the kings abſolute power, but by grant, and that alſo the ſame was in the time of warre, and to endure but two or three yeare, if the warre ſhould ſo long continue, as will beſt appear by the words of the Record. <hi>Cum cuſtuma</hi> 40<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 
               <hi>nobis in Subſidium guaerrae noſtrae contra Regem Franciae de quolibet ſacco lanae exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unte regnum noſtrum percipiendum per biennium vel triennium ſi tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duraſſet guerra illa nuper conceſſ. fuit, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:157030:26"/>
            <p> By this you perceive, by what means, upon what occaſion, and with what limittation this impoſition was laid: if you will further know, what followed of it, May it pleaſe you to read the Printed Statute of <hi>an.</hi> 21. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. where it is ſaid that the more part of the Commonalty found themſelves ſore agreeved therewithall; And by the ſame Statute, not only that impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of 40. ſhillings upon a ſack of wooll, which was the occaſion of the great grief &amp; complaint was taken away; but upon occaſion thereof, there was at the ſame time proviſion alſo made, againſt all other impoſitions whatſoever, as I ſay, I hope I ſhall anon cleerly prove unto you, Inſomuch as this impoſition of 40. ſhillings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſack of wooll, ought to be ſo farre from being urged as a preſident for the preſent impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and conſequently of the grievance of the Common wealth which followes thereupon, as that rather on the contrary part it may be thought to be the happieſt accident in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence thereof, that ever befell the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth in this kinde. For it was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the making of the firſt law that ever was made againſt impoſitions, and other charges and burdens of that nature to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the kings abſolute power without aſſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And ſo I leave their ſecond Preſident,<note place="margin">Vouched by <hi>Fleming, Clark, Dodderidge, Bacon, Attorny Hobart.</hi>
               </note> and come to the third, which in time was 31. <hi>of the ſame King E.</hi> 1. It is no other then that increaſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:157030:26"/> of Cuſtome, which by the Merchant ſtrangers was granted to king <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. by that Charter now familiarly known unto us by the name of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Mercatoria,</hi> which by all that have maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Majeſties right to impoſe, hath been ſtood upon and urged, as an impoſition by the kings abſolute power; but more eſpecially hath Maſter <hi>Solicitor</hi> been ſtrongly inforced with all the advantage poſſible for the maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his opinion. Nevertheleſſe I doubt not but I ſhall give it a very full anſwer, ſuch as yet this objection hath not received, though divers that have ſpoken before, and ſome this day, have undertaken to cleere it; wherein I will arrogate nothing to my ſelfe, but leave it wholly to your cenſure. It hath been ſaid by Maſter <hi>Solicitor,</hi> that though this increaſe of Cuſtome may ſeem to ſome, to proceed from the grant of Merchants, yet that this grant of theirs was to no other purpoſe, nor had other effect, then only thereby to declare their aſſent; For that, that thoſe which did grant were no Corporation or body in the eſtimation of Law, and ſo could not binde any but themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and not ſuch as ſhould ſucceed them. And that it was only the authority of the kings pleaſure to accept and take this increaſe of Cuſtome that gave it life at the firſt and ſtrength to continue as an Impoſition till this very day. For <hi>even at this day ſaith he, the 3. pence upon the pound granted by the ſaid Charter, is paid
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:157030:27"/> by the Merchants ſtrangers, and they likewiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſome priviledges granted by the ſaid Charter.</hi> And it was further by him obſerved; that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Statutes that have been ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt impoſitions, yet this impoſition hath continually ſtood and hath never been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to be paid by any man; And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is likely that no man till now ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that theſe Statutes were made againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon Merchandizes, but were rather to be underſtood to extend onely to impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within the Realme.</p>
            <p>To this objection,<note place="margin">27. E. 3. No. 27 13 E. 3. c. 26.</note> I make this Anſwer, that it is indeed true, that the grant of Merchants in this caſe, cannot binde the whole Common wealth; as I have heretofore proved by the Petition exhibited in Parliament by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons 27 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>No.</hi> 27. and by a Statute of 36 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 26. And therefore I cannot but confeſſe that this increaſe of cuſtome may very truely be called an impoſition, For that indeed it did at firſt take ſtrength, onely by the kings pleaſure to accept it (as hath been ſaid) and not by the grant of the Merchants, admitting it therefore to be a meer impoſition; Let us conſider with what extraordinary circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances it is accompanied.</p>
            <p>Firſt (as you may perceive by the Record it ſelf, and as it hath partly been ſaid already, the King took it not without yeelding recompence for it; For the Merchants ſtrangers, by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:157030:27"/> themſelves unto this charge, obtained divers liberties and immunities from the King, by the ſame Charter, amongſt which freedome from Priſage is one which at this day they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, In which reſpect this impoſition is in ſome ſort tollerable, though not at all Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Another conſiderable circumſtance, and difference from our preſent Impoſitions is this, that it was a compoſition made by the King with Merchant ſtrangers, which though it be by ſtrictneſſe of our common law, not of force to binde in perpetuitie; yet how farre by the Civill Law this doth binde ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which are governed by theſe lawes, is not ſo eaſily decided, and this may be a good co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to uphold it.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſpeciall reaſons, though they may well ſerve the turne, to make an evident difference betwixt this, and our preſent impoſitions, and ſo conſequently to avoid the concluſion, drawn from the Preſident, and may alſo ſeem colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and particular reaſons to uphold the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition it ſelf; yet is not this that which I mean to relie upon for Anſwer; For even this Impoſition, in recompence of which the King parted with ſo large priviledges and benefits, and which becauſe it concerned only merchant ſtrangers, did neither in the burden thereof, nor in the preſident, ſo directly touch the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> yet in the deteſtation, as it ſeems of all impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:157030:28"/> of what nature or kiude ſoever, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what pretext or colour ſoever they were grounded, I ſay, even this impoſition alſo was complained of in Parliament within few yeeres following; and upon complaint, taken away, as may appeare by the cloſe Roll of 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brana</hi> 23. Where you ſhall finde inrolled a <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſede as,</hi> commanding that the new Cuſtome, granted by the Merchant ſtrangers (reciting the particulars, as they are contained in <hi>Charta Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoria)</hi> ſhall ceaſe at the Kings pleaſure, and this is there ſaid to be yeelded to at the requeſt of the Commons which cannot be but in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; but becauſe the renewing of it again reſted at the Kings pleaſure, therefore within two yeeres after, by a publike Ordinance made by the principall Prelates, Earles and Barons, and other great men of the Kingdome, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed by the Kings Commiſſion, dated the 16. of <hi>May,</hi> the ſame third yeere of his reigne, the Charter it ſelfe was declared to be utterly void, For that it was hurtfull to the Commonwealth, againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and made <hi>without aſſent in Parliament;</hi> and not only that Charter, but all other new Cuſtomes or Impoſitions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, impoſed ſince the Coronation of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. till that time were alſo taken away, ſaving one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the old cuſtome upon Wooll, Wooll-felts, and Leather, And further it was ordained, That if any man ſhould preſume <hi>to take</hi> any more then the auncient cuſtom rightfully due,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:157030:28"/> and ſhould be thereof convict, he ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the partie greeved his Coſts and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, be impriſoned according to the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his offence, and be further puniſhed, as an offender againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> according to the diſcretion of the Juſtices. <hi>Ro. ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>in the Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the force and authoritie of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, may perhaps be doubted and blemiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed becauſe it was made by the Barons, at the time when they had the better hand of the King, as hath been in part objected, yet you ſee that they deliver not their cenſures, without alledging alſo their reaſons;<note place="margin">37. E. 3.20.</note> and this their Ordinance is no more in effect, then that which was thought fit by all the Commons in the Parliament of 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
            <p>But it hath been yet further ſaid, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Ordinance, the impoſition doth nevertheleſſe continue in force, and is at this day paid by the Merchant ſtrangers, and that therefore in likely hood, the ordinance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed not againſt it. Tis true that at this day the Merchant ſtranger doth pay three pence more in the pound for Subſidie of poundage, then the Engliſh doth, and that by vertue of <hi>Charta Mercatoria:</hi> But let me tell you that <hi>Charta Mercatoria</hi> in it ſelfe, had not ſtrength and vertue ſufficient to ſubſiſt for ſo long a time: It was as I have ſaid ſuſpended by the king him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:157030:29"/> 
               <hi>an.</hi> 3. condemned by the ordinance of 5 <hi>E.</hi> 2 and had at this day been of no more force, then it was all the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. after 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. that is, of none at all; had it not been confirmed by act of Parliament <hi>an.</hi> 36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> This was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which protected <hi>Charta Mercatoria</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all thoſe Statutes made againſt impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that hath kept it in life till this day; And this indeed (I mean an act of Parliament) is the only means that our Law acknowledgeth, for the laying or eſtabliſhing of impoſitions, and without which they cannot long laſt.</p>
            <p>You have now heard opened three of thoſe ſix preſidents, which are moſt relied upon for mantenance of theſe preſent impoſitions which are all that have been urged, or can be found to have been practiſed from the Conqueſt till the reigne of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. during which time there are as you ſee, as many publique acts in oppoſition of them, which are of ſo much the more force in that they are the Legall regular Acts of great Counſells, whereas on the contrary part, thoſe three impoſitions were the acts of powerfull Kings wills, in the times of extream neceſſity, As for <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Edw. 2.</note> his ſucceſſor, there hath not been one Impoſition alledged to have been laid by him of one kinde or other. Nay all the records touching this buſineſſe found in his time being onely foure make directly againſt them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>anno</hi> 3. which was (as you have heard) a releaſe at the Kings will, upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:157030:29"/> of the Commons, of the Impoſitions raiſed by <hi>Charta Mercatoria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond was the Ordinance made <hi>an.</hi> 5. declaring <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> and all other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to be void, and inflicting puniſhment upon ſuch as ſhould demand any.</p>
            <p>The third was, <hi>an.</hi> 11. which is a <hi>Superſede as</hi> to diſcharge certain co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities from yeelding an increaſe of Cuſtome granted by Merchants, by way of loane, which in great probability the King would never have releaſed, but upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint; the rather I think ſo, becauſe as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord recites, it was granted in a time of great neceſſity.</p>
            <p>The fourth is, <hi>anno</hi> 12. and is much of the ſame nature, the recitall of which containes ſome very obſervable things, which I will open unto you: It ſhewes firſt in very effectuall words the greatneſſe of the Kings wants, and the cauſes thereof, the words are, <hi>Cum pro ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditione guerrae noſtrae Scotiae, &amp; aliis arduis neceſſitatibus nobis multipliciter incumbentibus, pro quarum exoneratione quaſi infinitam pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam profundere oportebit, pecunia plurimum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeamus in preſenti; ac inſuper, pro eo quod exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Regni &amp; terrae noſtrae ſimul cum pecunia nobis in ſubventionem praemiſſorum tam pro Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quam pro Comunitatem Regni noſtri conceſſa ad ſumptus predictos cum feſtinationem qua ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediret faciend. non ſufficiunt:</hi> Here was cauſe, (if any cauſe may poſſibly be juſt) for the King
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:157030:30"/> preſently to put in practiſe his Prerogative of Impoſitions, his expence by reaſon of a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Warre in <hi>Scotland</hi> was ſo great, as the whole Revenue of the kingdome, together with an ayd which had been lately granted him, could not with that expedition that was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſupply his preſent want, doth hee for all this make uſe of his Prerogative of impoſing? or doth hee haſtily for want of adviſed procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, take ſome other courſe prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to his right? No, the record further ſayes, that he enquired by all wayes and meanes how he might moſt commodiouſly and fitly levy money for theſe occaſions. After which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed deliberation, the courſe at laſt reſolved upon, was not by abſolute power to lay Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, which of all other courſes (if it had been lawfull, had been the moſt ſpeedy and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall) but a courſe more juſtifiable; which was, that Merchants ſhould be called together, and that they ſhould be intreated to lend the King upon every ſack of wooll 10. ſhillings and upon every laſt of Lether 5. ſhillings, above the ancient cuſtome, and that for their ſecurity of true repayment, <hi>without fiction or delay,</hi> which are the words of the Record, (whereby it ſeems that onely a pretence of a Loane and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment had been before that time uſed to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour Impoſitions, commandment ſhould be given to the Cuſtomers to certifie into the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, the names of every particular Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:157030:30"/> that ſhould ſo lend unto the King, that they might accordingly receive full ſatisfaction. And tis worth the obſerving, that this Loane was for no longer time, Then from Aprill, till October following; thus much is warranted by the Record: So as you ſee that in all this time of this <hi>King, Ed.</hi> 2. Impoſitions were not only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together forborn even in the times of his greateſt neceſſity, but they were alſo condemned as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and utterly unlawfull.</p>
            <p>We come now to the reigne of <hi>King Ed.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Ed. 3.</note> in whoſe time there was no practiſe or meanes, that by the policy of man could be thought on to bring the people under this yoke of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, without aſſent of Parliament, but it was by him attempted: Inſomuch, as I have in my obſervation out of the Records collected no leſſe then five or ſix ſeverall waies all of them very colourable, which in his time were put in practiſe for the raiſing of impoſitions, and yet none of them but was reſiſted by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condemned.</p>
            <p>That which was moſt uſuall with him was that Merchants ſhould grant to pay him ſo much upon every Commodity exported or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by way of increaſe of Cuſtome;<note place="margin">Impoſitions by way of Grant of Merchants.</note> this ſeems not unreaſonable, for that every man might grant of his own what he liſted, and this alſo to make it more colourable was never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, but in the time of warre: And yet as it hath been pastly ſaid already, this was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:157030:31"/> held unlawfull, as may appeare by the Record of 17 <hi>E.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">17 E. 3. No. 27. Ro. Parl.</note> where the Commons in Parliament ſay that it is a great miſchiefe, and againſt reaſon, that they ſhould be enforced to pay the deerer for Commodities, by reaſon of a charge upon Merchandizes, by the grant of Merchants, <hi>anno</hi> 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">25 E. 3. No. 22. Ro. Parl.</note> the which is a charge to the people, though none to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant; the Commons reciting, that whereas Merchants have granted a new increaſe of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to the King, pray that Commiſſions to collect ſuch new increaſe of Cuſtome, by ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler grant of Merchants be not awarded, <hi>anno</hi> 36 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. (Amongſt the printed Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes) Grants of Subſidies upon Woolls by Merchants without aſſent of Parliament are declared to be void, which act was made upon a Petition of the Commons in <hi>anno</hi> 36 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. deſiring a Law to be made to the ſame effect. If impoſitions raiſed by the Grant of Merchants,<note place="margin">36 E. 3. No 26. Ro. Parl.</note> (which I ſuppoſe to have been by ſome publike and ſolemne inſtrument, under the hands and ſeals of the principall Merchants of all the great Towns of <hi>England,</hi> being called together for that purpoſe; were not of force in this behalf) much leſſe, was their bare aſſent without any ſuch ſolemnity, which alſo was a courſe in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in the dayes of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. And was alſo uſed in the laying of theſe preſent impoſitions, which wee now complaine of.</p>
            <p>Another meanes of raiſing impoſitions uſed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:157030:31"/> by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. was by way of diſpenſation for money with ſome Statute in force,<note place="margin">Impoſitions by way of Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with a penal Law.</note> which reſtrained the paſſage of Merchants; moſt of his impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of one kinde or other, laid after 11. were of this nature, for <hi>anno</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. amongſt the printed Statutes, you ſhall finde it enacted, that <hi>no man upon paine of Death, loſſe of Lands, and Goods ſhould export Wools:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stat 11. Ed. 3. cap. 1.</note> imediately after the making of this Statute Impoſitions, by way of Diſpenſations for money, came to be ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and burdenſome that the very yeere fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the King being in perſon to undertake a Warre in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and for the raiſing of treaſure having laid heavy impoſitions in this kinde, which he perceived to be very burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the people; he wrote to the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (his Letter is extant upon Record) to this effect; that whereas the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were much burdened with divers charges, tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12 E. 3. No. 22. Ro. Aleman.</note> 
               <hi>and impoſitions (which he could not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but with much griefe) but being enforced by inevitable neceſſity could not as yet eaſe the people of them, he required the Arch-biſhop to exhort the people patiently and humbly to beare the burden for a while, and to excuſe him towards the people, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping he ſhould ere long recompence his ſaid people, and give them comfort in due time.</hi> His neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were nevertheleſſe ſo great, and this means of raiſing money was ſo colourable (ſeeing no man was compelled to pay that did not himſelf deſire to be diſpenſed with, for the breach of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:157030:32"/> a penall Law, by which his life, goods and lands were forfeited) as he ſpared not to lay on load in this kinde; Inſomuch as you ſhall finde that in <hi>An.</hi> 13. he took for diſpenſations to paſſe only to <hi>Antwerp</hi> of Engliſh-men 40.<note place="margin">13 Ed. 3. Orig. de Scac. Ro. 3. &amp; 12.</note> ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings upon a ſack of Wooll, 40. ſhilllings upon 300. Wooll-fells, and 4. pound upon a Laſt of Leather; Of ſtrangers 3. pound upon a Sack of Wooll, 3. pound upon 300. Wooll-fells, and 6. pound for a Laſt of Leather, whereas the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and due cuſtome was no more then 6. ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings upon a ſack of Wooll, the like upon 300. Wooll-fells, and 13. ſhillings 4. pence upon a Laſt of Leather;<note place="margin">13 Ed. 3. no. 5. Ro. Parliam.</note> Immediately hereupon, even this very yeere, was this complained of in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and a Petition exibited by the Lords and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, that it might be enacted, that this <hi>Maletolt</hi> or Impoſition, becauſe it was taken without aſſent of Parliament, might be taken away, and that a Law might be made, that no ſuch charge might be laid, but by aſſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: And they further prayed, that they might have a Charter under the great Seal, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and enrolled in Parliament, to the ſame effect, which was performed the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as may appeare by the Statutes printed, where, <hi>An.</hi> 14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.<note place="margin">14. Ed 3. cap. 21.</note> you ſhall ſee an act of Parliament to this effect, and that a moſt effectuall one. And immediately after, follows the Charter to the ſame effect, of both which I ſhall have more occaſion to ſpeak hereafter;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:157030:32"/> But ſuch were the Kings wants, that even in the meane time, between the petition, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the act, he could not forbeare to raiſe money by this meanes, For in <hi>An.</hi> 14, the Eleventh day of <hi>March,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14. Ed. 3. Ro. 3. <hi>orig. de Scac.</hi>
               </note> in the end of which moneth the next Parliament began (as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the Preamble to the Statutes of that Parliament) he tooke by way of diſpenſation, 40. ſhillings upon a ſack of Wooll, when it ſhould be ſafely landed at <hi>Bruxells,</hi> and 40. ſhillings at the port within <hi>England,</hi> which was indeed an intollerable charge: but the better to colour it, the King in his Commiſſions for col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection thereof, pretended that the Merchants had been humble ſuiters to him, that the paſſage for Woolls might be open till <hi>Whitſontide</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and that to obtaine the ſame, they had of their free wills offered to give him the ſaid ſummes, as may appeare by the recitall, in the beginning of the ſaid Record.</p>
            <p>In further prevention of this miſchiefe,<note place="margin">Stat. 27. E. 3. cap. 2.</note> in an Act of Parliament printed, made <hi>An.</hi> 27. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. there was a ſpeciall proviſion made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Licenſes to Tranſport: Nevertheleſſe as it may be collected by a Record of the ſame yeere, the King raiſed 40. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig. de Scac.</hi> 27. E. 3. Ro. 7.</note> ſhillings upon a ſack of Wooll, 40. ſhillings upon 300. Wooll-fells, and 4. Pound upon a Laſt of Leather, by the ſame means (I meane by way of diſpenſation.) For though indeed it be recited to be granted by Merchants, yet was it no otherwiſe granted
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:157030:33"/> by them, then for Licenſes to tranſport, For at that time the Staple of Wooll was in <hi>England,</hi> as may appeare by the printed Statute of 27. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. &amp; 2.<note place="margin">27 Ed 3. cap. 1. &amp;. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And here I thinke it fit to make this obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in generall, that whereas in ſome other of the Records of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. there is mention made of Impoſitions upon Woolls, granted by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, becauſe the paſſage of Woolls was in thoſe daies ſo often reſtrained by Statute, as may appeare by very many printed Statutes of that time, it is very likely that theſe grants of Merchants, were alſo for diſpenſations to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,<note place="margin">Yet you ſhall finde an act of Parlia. for free paſſage. <hi>An.</hi> 15. Ed. 3.</note> as appears that this of 27. was, and it may well be, that ſome of the Statutes, being but temporary, were not committed to the Preſſe; This kinde of Impoſition, by way of diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I finde not to have been at all practiſed from 27. till 39. where without any colouring of the matter, with pretence of the grant or guift of Merchants, or any recitall of ſuite made by Merchants, to have the paſſage open, as uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in former times,<note place="margin">39. Ed. 3. Ro. 2. <hi>Orig. Scacario.</hi>
               </note> but plainly and aptly the King recites, <hi>That whereas Engliſh Merchants were by Act of Parliament reſtrained to tranſport Woolls, Nevertheleſſe, upon advice with his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, he thought fit to give leave that ſuch as would, might tranſport Wolls, paying</hi> 46. <hi>ſhillings</hi> 8. <hi>pence upon a ſacke, which the King commandeth to be levied.</hi> This Impoſition laſted a very little while, For the next Parliament following, the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:157030:33"/> Subjects granted to the King a Subſidie, upon Woolls, Wooll-fells, and Leather, to endure for a very ſhort time; and yet, as it appears by the words of the Record, the King doth thank his people for it, <hi>with all his heart:</hi> at which time, for the maintenance of his warres in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he obtaineth the continuance thereof <hi>for two yeeres,</hi> at the end of which <hi>two yeers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">43. Ed. 3.9 &amp; 10 Ro. Parl.</note> he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obtaineth, in Parliament, a continuance of the ſame from <hi>Michaelmas</hi> following, <hi>for three yeeres,</hi> for the ſupplie of treaſure for the warre. Two yeers following, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>An.</hi> 45.<note place="margin">Num. 42. Rl. o. Parliam.</note> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons doubting, as it ſeemeth, that the King had ſecretly concluded to increaſe (by way of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition) this Subſidie, which was yeelded to in Parliament, and granted for three yeeres, made a conditionall petition, that if any Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be laid upon Woolls, Wooll-fells, or Leather, more then the Subſidie granted in Parliament, that it may be taken away: the King anſwereth, That if any be laid ſince the Statute, it ſhall be taken away; and then follows the printed Statute, <hi>An.</hi> 45. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>That no Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions be laid upon Woolls, wooll-fells, or Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> which is the firſt place where I finde <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> named in our printed Books; I finde them firſt named upon my Latine Record, 12. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. in the Kings Letter to the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: and firſt upon any Record in French, not printed, <hi>An.</hi> 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 16. <hi>Ro. Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:157030:34"/>
            <p> But to proceed: about a yeere following this Parliament of 45. (neere which time, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie granted, <hi>An.</hi> 43.<note place="margin">46. Ed. 3. Nu. 10. Ro. Parl.</note> for three yeeres, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired) there was another Subſidie of Forty three ſhillings foure pence upon a ſack of wooll, as much upon Twelve ſcore Wooll-fells, and Five pounds upon a Laſt of Leather, above the ancient cuſtomes, granted in Parliament, for the maintainance of the warre in <hi>Guyen,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for two yeers; For which, the King like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe gave thanks.</p>
            <p>The next yeer following, the Subſidie gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the laſt Parliament,<note place="margin">46. Ed. 3. Nu. 12 Ro. Parl.</note> was continued from <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> for a yeere, without any conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for the next yeere, upon condition (amongſt other things) That no Impoſition be laid during the two yeeres,<note place="margin">48. E. 3. Ro. 2. <hi>Orig. de Scac.</hi>
               </note> and that the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney levied, be imployed upon the warres. In the next yeere following, the King took, as by the grant of Merchants, upon a ſack of Wooll, of Denizens Fifty ſhillings, and of ſtrangers foure Marks; upon 240. Wooll-fells, of Denizens Fifty ſhillings, and of Strangers Foure Marks, and upon every Laſt of Leather, of Denizens Five pounds, and of Strangers Eight Marks; Though this Record pretendeth nothing but the grant of Merchants, yet it is upon the matter no other then a diſpenſation for ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, For at this time, the paſſage was not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, other then to <hi>Callice,</hi> where the ſtaple then was, as may appeare by the two Records of 38.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:157030:34"/> 
               <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Ro. Parl. &amp;</hi> 50. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 24. And yet you may ſee how hatefull, even theſe Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by way of Diſpenſation (which are farre more tollerable then our preſent Impoſitions) were in thoſe dayes: For within two yeeres following, one <hi>Richard Lions,</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin">5<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Farmer of the Cuſtomes (amongſt other things laid to his charge) was accuſed in Parliament for ſetting or procuring to be ſet, new impoſitions (not ſhewing of what nature) without aſſent of Parliament, and was adjudged to forfeit his Goods and Lands;<note place="margin">50 E. 3. N. Ro. Parl.</note> but more particularly the Lord <hi>Latymer,</hi> Lord Chamberlaine of <hi>England,</hi> was expreſly accuſed, that he combined with <hi>Richard Lions</hi> and others, who for their own profit, had procured and Counſelled the King to grant many Licences for the tranſporting of great quantities of Wooll beyond the Seas, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to the Staple at <hi>Callice,</hi> againſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Ordinances and Commandements to the contrary, and had put upon Wools and Wool-fells new impoſitions; Here you ſee that the device of Diſpenſations for money, had the name of an Impoſition in thoſe dayes, though indeed it be not in its nature a meere impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at leaſt not ſuch a one as thoſe are which we complain of: But ſuch as it was, you ſee how from time to time it hath beene condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and how it is reckoned up amongſt the moſt hainous faults of thoſe two great offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who though perhaps they were condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:157030:35"/> alſo for other offences, yet the laying of theſe to their charge, did ſhew the great hate generally conceived againſt impoſitions of this kinde; I might here further adde in proofe of the invalidity of theſe Diſpenſations, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Merchants having obtained ſome of theſe, and having alſo the advantage of the Kings Proclamation to diſpenſe with the Statute, which reſtrained their paſſage, yet they never thought themſelves ſecure from ths puniſhment of the Statute, till they were provided for by Act of Parliament, as may appeare by a Statute printed, <hi>anno</hi> 35 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. To alledge therefore any of this kind, thereby to prove the lawfulnes of ours cannot but argue a weak cauſe.</p>
            <p>For firſt (as I have ſaid) there is farre more reaſon and colour for theſe, then for ours; for in this caſe no man was compelled to pay, that did it not to avoide a greater miſcheife, for by paying the Impoſition, he was free from a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veous puniſhment for breach of a penall Law, which reſtrained his paſſage; whereas in our caſe a charge is laid upon him for exerciſing his lawfull Trade, where no Statute Law, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law is to the contrary, but rather both the one and the other make for him.</p>
            <p>But it may bee here objected, that the King may Lawfully reſtraine, the breach of which reſtraint, is a contempt and againſt Law, and that to impoſe doth imply a reſtraint upon a penalty. Suppoſe it were ſo, yet if in caſe where
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:157030:35"/> the reſtraint is not onely by the King, but the whole Eſtate aſſembled in Parliament, for ſome urgent cauſe it be unlawfull to give Licenſe for money (as you perceive it is) how much more is it ſo, where the reſtraint is for no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then to raiſe an impoſition as in our caſe; but of this more largely hereafter.</p>
            <p>Another deviſe of raiſing impoſitions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſſent of the Commons in Parliament,<note place="margin">Impoſitions raiſed by way of Ordinance in Parliament</note> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. was <hi>by way of Ordinance,</hi> which indeed is in the next degree of ſtrength unto a Statute. For it is a Conſtitution made by the king himſelfe, and all the Prelates, Earls, and Barons, not at the Counſell Table, or in the Kings Chamber; but ſitting ſolemnly in Parliament, and hath alſo the like ſolemnity of inrolement that a Statute hath, onely it is enrolled in a Roll by it ſelfe, which hath the name of the Roll of the Ordinances; But the only eſſentiall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between this and an Act of Parliament, is, that this hath not the aſſent of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>Some Ordinances have had that eſtimation amongſt us, that they have at this day; the force of Statutes as the Ordinance of <hi>Merton,</hi> made 20 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. (which though it were no other then an Ordinance made by the King, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Earls, and Barons, without aſſent of the Commons, yet hath it by continuance of time gotten not onely the ſtrength, but the name alſo of a Statute. There be ſome others of this by
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:157030:36"/> nature, and we finde it uſuall, that the names of Statutes and Ordinances, have been Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and confuſedly uſed, to expreſſe the one or the other. So as there was not any other more probable deviſe or invention to have brought the people under the yoake of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without their own aſſent, then was this, by the way of Ordinance; Nay to adde yet a further ſtrength to this high authority of an Ordinance in Parliament, the aſſent alſo of Merchants was uſually joyned therewithall, to make it have the cleerer paſſage with the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and further it was never, but in the time of warre.</p>
            <p>The firſt impoſition of this kinde by way of Ordinance,<note place="margin">7 Ed. 3. R 9. Orig. de Scac.</note> which I finde amongſt the Records was 7 <hi>E.</hi> 3. amongſt the Originals of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, where it is ſaid by way of recitall, that the King conſidering how Merchants (which make great gaine by trading) ought aſwell as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to aſſiſt him with treaſure for his Warre, eſpecially conſidering how at their intreaty he had placed the ſtaple in <hi>England:</hi> Therefore at his Parliament held at <hi>Yorke,</hi> by the Prelates, Earls and Barons, it was ordained that the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhould yeeld unto the King a Subſidie upon Merchandizes: This Subſidie or rather Impoſition, thus ſolemnly ordained, and in the times of ſo great neceſſity, was no ſooner eſtabliſhed then revoked, as may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ppeare by the words imediately following in the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:157030:36"/> whereupon the Merchants of their own accords yeelded, and freely gave ten ſhillings upon a ſack of Wooll, as much upon three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Woolfels, and twenty ſhillings upon laſt of Lether, for a ſhort time by way of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation or Licence towards the maintenance of the Warre.</p>
            <p>The like is found, <hi>anno</hi> 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">20. Ed. 3. Nu. 18. Ro Parl.</note> where the Commons complaining of an impoſition of this kinde, laid by the Prelates, Earles, and Barons in Parliament, and by the agreement alſo of Merchants; It was not denyed unto them, but that their ſuit was juſt; onely it was anſwered them, that as yet it was not convenient to take it away; For that the King had taken up great ſummes of money of divers Merchants, for his preſent neceſſity, to be repayed out of the ſaid Subſidie, and therefore it could not be as yet diſcharged without great damage to the King and the Merchants. But the moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Record againſt Impoſitions by way of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, is the yeere following, where the King in excuſe of impoſitions complained of, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth that they were laid in times of great neceſſity, <hi>and by the aſſent of the Prelates, Earles and Barons, and other great men, and ſome of the Commons then preſent, nevertheleſſe his pleaſure is, that ſuch impoſitions</hi> not duly laid, <hi>be not drawn into conſequence, but taken away</hi> 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>No.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>There are ſome others of this kinde, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:157030:37"/> any that did abide the triall, though they have allwayes been accompanied with all ſuch circumſtances, as were moſt likely to give them paſſage without controllment, as to be laid in the time of warre, to be limited to a ſhort time, with conſent of Merchants. If the authoritie of an Ordinance in Parliament, joyned with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Merchants, were in thoſe dayes not of force ſufficient to uphold Impoſitions, much leſſe will an Order of the King and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell out of Parliament, uphold them at this day, eſpecially after ſo many yeeres diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>Another invention to raiſe impoſitions,<note place="margin">Impoſitions rayſed by way of Loane by Merchants.</note> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and in former times, was by way of a pretended or feined Loane from the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, of ſo much above the old cuſtome upon Merchandiſe exported or imported, which Loane was never repaid to the Merchant. That this was an old practiſe, may be collected by the preſident, 12. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. already cited, where the King promiſeth, that <hi>without fiction,</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, he would repay them their money, imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, that ſometimes fiction had been uſed, and doubtleſſe that loane which was 11. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. the very yeere before, was ſuch a fained Loane as I ſpeake of, for otherwiſe (without queſtion) the King would not have releaſed part of it, as may appeare by that Record that he did; For if the money be, <hi>bona fide,</hi> borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and truly intended to be repaid, then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:157030:37"/> the courſe is lawfull; if otherwiſe, I hold this kinde alſo as unlawfull as any of the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the Third did once or twice borrow in this kinde, as may appeare by Records alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cited to another purpoſe, with which I will not againe trouble you.</p>
            <p>There was yet another Device for raiſing of Impoſitions (begun indeed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Impoſitions raiſed by grant of Merchants, for Liberties granted to them.</note> but revived, and much practiſed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. which was alſo by way of grant of Merchants, and yet not altogether the ſame that I firſt obſerved to have been ſo much practiſed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. but is much more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable and tollerable. For whereas that was a grant, or rather a meere guift, without any thing granted back againe in lieu thereof; this I now ſpeake of, is a ſolemne grant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, made by Merchants, of an increaſe of cuſtome, for liberties and freedoms, and other valuable priviledges, and exemptions, granted unto them by the King: that former was, <hi>date nihil expectantes;</hi> this is, <hi>date &amp; dabitur vobis,</hi> and indeed the recompence that the Merchants had by this Charter granted unto them, made their grant to the King leſſe ſubject to controll, then otherwiſe without ſuch recompence it would have been; I mean the grant of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſtrangers, ſo often remembred amongſt us, by the name of <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> which though it were damned all the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:157030:38"/> from the third yeer of his reign, yet was it revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>E.</hi> 3. (<hi>Even that very yeer, when he likewiſe depoſed the King his father,</hi> and uſurped to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe his Crown.)For it appeares by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, that he commanded the ſame to be levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the very firſt yeere of his Reigne.<note place="margin">1. Ed. 3. Ro. Fin.</note> What hath been ſaid againſt this kind of Impoſition, I ſhall not need here againe to repeate, only let me call to your remembrance, how this Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as needing a better prop then his owne ſtrength, and Validity in Law, was in the ſame Kings Reigne confirmed by Parliament, and onely by that ſtrength continueth in force at this day.</p>
            <p>You have heard five or ſixe ſeverall politique Inventions and Deviſes for the eaſie drawing on, and ſweetning of this yoak of Impoſitions, all practiſed by this prudent and potent King, <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. whoſe times were indeed ſo troubleſom, and his charge every way ſo exceſſive, as it is no marvell, that he left not any way unattempted, to raiſe money, without the aſſent of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, whom he always found unwillingly and hardly drawne to matters of charge.</p>
            <p>One other way of Impoſitions he uſed,<note place="margin">Impoſitions laid by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</note> not coloured or masked under any ſuch pretence, or politick Invention, as you have heard, but plain and direct, only his owne expreſſe command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Officers, to collect of every Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſo much for ſuch a commoditie, exported or imported, and to anſwere it into his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:157030:38"/> without any recitall in his Commiſſions, of Grant, Aſſent, Guift, Loane of Merchants, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation, or Ordinance in Parliament, or any other ſuch colourable pretext what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            <p>Theſe indeed, and onely theſe are meer Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and may be aptly compared with theſe of our times; Of this kind, amongſt all the Records of <hi>Edward</hi> the Thirds time, I finde on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two, which I will truly open unto you; The firſt is in the Twenty one of his Reigne, where it appears that <hi>Lionell</hi> afterwards <hi>Duke of Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> named upon the Record,<note place="margin">21. Ed. 3 no 11 Ro. Parliam.</note> 
               <hi>Lionell of Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp,</hi> becauſe I ſuppoſe, he was there borne, the Kings ſecond ſonne being then Guardian of <hi>England,</hi> whileſt the King his father was at the ſiege of <hi>Callice,</hi> at a counſell by him held the ſame yeere, which I take to be no other then the Privie Counſell, aſſeſſed without aſſent of Parliament, upon every ſack of Wooll Two Shillings, upon every Tun of Wine Two Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, upon every Pound of Aver de poys of Merchandizes imported,<note place="margin">Poundage impoſed.</note> Sixe pence. This Impoſition was, I muſt confeſſe (for ought I know to the contrary) ſuch as our preſent Impoſitions are, I meane, in that it was impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed onely, and ſimply by the Kings abſolute power, and may in that reſpect be the Fourth (of that number of Sixe) which I told you were all that could be found in any degree like to ours, ever to have been practiſed in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:157030:39"/> from the Conqueſt, till Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time. But though in the authoritie of impoſing, it be like, yet in circumſtances very materiall, you ſhall finde an apparant difference between them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, this Impoſition is very moderate in the ſum, as you may perceive, for it was but Two Shillings upon a ſack, whereas in 13. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. forty Shillings upon a ſack of wooll was uſuall, and ſometimes fifty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it was to continue no longer then till Michaelmas following.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it was laid in the time of a moſt chargeable warre, and ordained to be imployed for the maintenance of Ships of warre at Sea, for the ſafeguard of Merchants in their paſſage, of which it is apparant, there was at this inſtant very great neceſſitie; for it was (as I have ſaid) impoſed then, when King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. lay at the ſiege of <hi>Callice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, ſuch as it was, and ſo qualified as you perceive, it was nevertheleſſe complained of in Parliament, by a Petition from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as may appeare be the Records of the ſame Parliament <hi>of</hi> 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. To which Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition or complaint, this anſwere was given, <hi>That all the ſaid Impoſitions were already taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſave only the Two Shillings upon a ſack of Wooll, which ſhould laſt no longer then Eaſter, and ſeeing the ſame was ordained for the ſafeguard of merchants, in which there had been greater ſums of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:157030:39"/> money expended by the King, then could be collected between that and Michaelmas, therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the ſame till Eaſter, he hoped it would not ſeem over-burdenſome or grieveous unto them.</hi> In the Parliament following, <hi>viz. anno</hi> 22. the Commons pray that writs may bee directed to the Cuſtomers to forbeare at Eaſter next to take the two ſhillings upon a ſack,<note place="margin">22 E. 3. N 16. Ro. Par.</note> according as it was granted at the laſt Parliament, and that it be not any longer continued by the procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Merchant. The King anſwereth, <hi>Let it ceaſe at Eaſter, as it was agreed the laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you ſee it was abſolutely taken away, and therefore though it had wanted theſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications and circumſtances which I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it had, yet it being a thing ſo publiquely condemned, it ought to be of little force with you to juſtifie theſe preſent Impoſitions. But that which I obſerve out of this laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, maketh me rather to incline that this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was onely by way of diſpenſation, then that it was an abſolute Impoſition, ſuch as Ours are. For to what end (I pray you) ſhould the Commons pray that it might not be any longer continued by the procurement of any Merchant, except it were likely that Merchants for their benefit ſhould pray the longer continuance thereof; and what benefit can any impoſition whatſoever bee to a Merchant except it bee by way of Diſpenſation
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:157030:40"/> to give him leave to trade where before ſuch diſpenſation given, he ſtood altogether reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. If then it be an Impoſition by way of diſpenſation with a penall Statute of reſtraint, then is it no preſident for our preſent impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But whether or no it be a Diſpenſation or abſolute Impoſition I leave it to your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; you have heard my obſervation.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the next preſident in the times of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. produced for maintenance of our Impoſitions,<note place="margin">24 E. 3. N. 12. Orig. de Scac.</note> which was in the 24 yeere of his Reigne, the Record of which and that which followed thereupon, I will without any inforcement at all, open unto you, and ſo leave it to your cenſures. The King reciting, that whereas the Spanyard and French had joyned in league to make Warre againſt him, and that for the withſtanding of his ſaid adverſaries, as alſo for the ſafeguard of Merchants againſt Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, he had ordained that certaine ſhips ſhould be ſet forth; and that for maintenance of the ſaid Ships, there ſhould be paid by Merchants two ſhillings for every ſack of Wooll, two ſhillings for three hundred Woolfels, foure ſhillings for a laſt of Lether, a Scute of Gold, or foure ſhil.<note place="margin">Poundage im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</note> for a tunne of Wine, and ſix pence of the pound upon all other Merchandizes for one yeere following. He commandeth his Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to levy the ſame accordingly.</p>
            <p>The very next yeere and Parliament follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">25 Ed 3. No. 12 Rot Par.</note> the Commons exhibite a Petition in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:157030:40"/> againſt Impoſitions and other like charges, without aſſent of Parliament: To which anſwer is given that, <hi>it is</hi> not <hi>the Kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they ſhould be charged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now gone through all the materiall Records here amongſt us, of the times of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. in which, though his reign were very long, and by reaſon of his Warres, and other exceſſive charge, more occaſion was given him to try the ſtrength of this point of the Prerogative, then ever any King before or ſince; though often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and by many politicke inventions (as you have heard) he attempted to eſtabliſh this Prerogative, of laying impoſitions without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in Parliament; yet can there not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in all his time, any more then two Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of Impoſitions like to theſe of ours; (that is) <hi>impoſed by the Kings abſolute authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> and yet theſe two were alſo, as you perceive, qualified with ſuch circumſtances, as if ours were ſuch, we ſhould have held them tolerable though perhaps not lawfull, yet they, ſuch as they were, eſcaped not without being complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of, and condemned alſo in Parliament, as you have heard.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be that ſome one or two of theſe Impoſitions which were by aſſent or grant of Merchants, in this time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. were in times when the paſſage was open, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by act of Parliament, and ſo to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to our impoſitions: but whoſoever ſhall
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:157030:41"/> by looking over the Statutes and Records with never ſo much heed conſider the times of opening and ſhutting of the Sea by Statutes, ſhall finde it ſo intricate, as hee ſhall bee very hardly able directly to ſay, that at the time when any of theſe impoſitions were granted, the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was open.</p>
            <p>If in my obſervation I had found any ſuch, I ſhould have admitted it for an abſolute impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, as I have done <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> which was by grant of Merchants; For certainly (as I have yeelded) the grant of Merchants is in this caſe of no other effect, then the declaration on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their aſſent; and the Impoſition reſteth meerly upon the kings authority: But I finde none ſuch, if any ſuch could be produced, you have heard how they have beene from time to time controlled in Parliament.</p>
            <p>And ſo I paſſe from <hi>E.</hi> 3. to the times follow. From the end of the Reign of <hi>E.</hi> 3. till the reign of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> who was the eleventh Prince of this Realme, after <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. (as <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. was the eleventh after the Conqueſt) being the ſpace of 170. yeers or thereabouts. It hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by all thoſe that have argued in mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his Majeſties Right to Impoſe, that there hath not been found one Record that proves any one impoſition to have been laid; there are indeed in our printed bookes ſome three or foure Statutes during that time, in which mention is made of Impoſitions, but
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:157030:41"/> they are (as I ſhall prove) Impoſitions of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature then thoſe are which we complaine of; and ſo make nothing at all to the proofe of his Majeſties Right: or if they were ſuch as ours are, yet are they no where found mentioned but with diſgrace, and to the end to be taken away, which may be the reaſon, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great uſe that might have been made of three or foure Preſidents of Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in theſe times, for the patching up of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the practiſe, which otherwiſe by this long diſcontinuance receives a great ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh: thoſe which argued for impoſitions did not take hold of theſe, but choſe rather to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that no Impoſitions at all were laid during all this time, and labored to ſeek out the reaſons of the diſcontinuance.</p>
            <p>I will briefely ſhew you what Statutes they are, during that time which, mention impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the firſt is, 11 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.<note place="margin">11 R. 2. cap. 9. Statutes in which there is mention made of Impoſitions after the end of Edw. the thirds raigne untill Queen Maries <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note> No Impoſition nor charge ſhall be put upon Wools, Lether, or Woolfels, other than the Cuſtome and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie granted to the King this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and if any be, the ſame ſhall be repealed and annulled, as it was another time ordained by Statute, ſaving alway to the King his anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent right. If by this ſaving the pretended right of impoſing ſhould be excepted (as was ſaid in the Exchequer) the ſaving ſhould then be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the body of the Act, and therefore it muſt needs have ſome other interpretation, that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:157030:42"/> it may ſtand with the reſt of the Act, and not condemn the Law makers of ſo much want of diſcretion: therefore doubtleſſe this (ſaving) is no other then an exception of the ancient Right, full Cuſtomes, due upon thoſe ſtaple Commodities. And for my part I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that the Statute was made, not ſo much to take away any Impoſition laid by this King <hi>R.</hi> 2. as out of a provident and prudent care in the Law makers, proceeding from the freſh memory of the practiſe of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. in this kinde; For all thoſe that were of this Parliament, did live and were at mans age in <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. time, and could not but well remember the grievouſnes of his Impoſitions: Beſides, I obſerve that they deſire, that no Impoſition be laid by way of addition to the Subſidie, upon Wools and Lether then granted: It was never heard till of late, that an Impoſition upon any Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, was charged at the ſame time with a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie, and therefore without queſtion, this was no other then an aboundant proviſion by them wherein they were no more carefull then any wiſe man would be in the like caſe; when they had of their own free wils given the King a liberall gift, they were carefull not to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charged by him.</p>
            <p>The next Statute in theſe times, where Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are found mentioned is, 23 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.<note place="margin">23 H. 6. cap. 18.</note> By which it appeares that Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants being reſtrained from repayring to <hi>G<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcoigne</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:157030:42"/> and <hi>Guien,</hi> to buy the Wines of that Country, they were nevertheleſſe ſuffered to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire thither paying certaine <hi>new Impoſitions,</hi> which were dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of them. Upon complaint hereof, it was enacted that all Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants might freely paſſe into thoſe parts, and buy Wines there at their pleaſure without any <hi>new Impoſition</hi> or charge to be put upon them; For that <hi>ſuch Impoſitions were to the damage of Merchants, and to the hinderance of all the Kings people: if any were demanded by the King Officers, the officers ſo demanding them ſhould forfeit twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pound, beſides treble damages to the party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe Impoſitions were by way of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation with a Statute, which reſtrained the repaire of Engliſh Merchants into thoſe parts, and not by the kings abſolute power, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to ground an Impoſition, is evident by the Statutes in Print. For from 27 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">27. E. 3. c. 6. 38. Ed. 3. c. 10 &amp; 38 Ed. 3. cap. 42 E. 3. cap. 8. 43 E. 3. c. 12.</note> till this 23 <hi>H.</hi> 6. there are five, or ſixe Statutes in Print to this purpoſe ſome more ſtrict then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which continued in force till 23 <hi>H.</hi> 6. The reaſon of the reſtraint by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. I ſuppoſe to have been becauſe <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> and <hi>Guien</hi> were then in his poſſeſſion, and he was deſirous his Subjects, the Merchants of thoſe Countries ſhould have the ſole profit of their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities; and that they onely ſhould import them into England, and not the Merchants of England: whatſoever the cauſe of the reſtraine
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:157030:43"/> was, it is very cleer <hi>the reſtraint was by Statute,</hi> and that this Impoſition raiſed by way of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation was condemned, which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe (ſuppoſe it had not been controled) yet as I have ſaid oftentimes, it is in nature ſo farre differing from ours, as the practiſe thereof will not ſo much as help to ſalve this long diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</p>
            <p>The next mention of Impoſitions is found, 1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">1 R. 3. cap. 12.</note> The words are, <hi>the Subjects and Cominalty of this Realme ſhall not from henceforth be charged by any ſuch charge or Impoſition called a Benevolence, nor by ſuch like charge;</hi> you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by the words of the Statute, what Impoſitions are intended within that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</p>
            <p>The next mention of Impoſitions in theſe times, I finde to be, 7 <hi>H.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">7 H. 7. cap. 7.</note> where a charge of eightteen ſhillings, laid upon a But of Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſie by Parliament is called an Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Another mention of Impoſitions, I finde to be 12 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">12 H: 7. cap. 6.</note> In the preamble of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute; the words are, <hi>That every perſon ought to uſe himſelfe to his moſt advantage without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, Fine, Impoſition or contribution to be had, or taken of him, to, or by any Engliſh perſon, or perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though ſome that have argued before me againſt Impoſitions have urged this Statute, as making againſt our preſent Impoſitions, yet
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:157030:43"/> for my part, I am not of that opinion, but upon peruſing the Statute, doe rather thinke, that it extendeth only to impoſitions laid by the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>London,</hi> upon the Merchants of other Cities and Townes not incorporate into their Companies, as will evidently appeare by the Statute: ſo as notwithſtanding this Statute, that which I have averred, and hath been yeelded to by the Kings Counſell, that no Impoſition was laid from <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. to Queene <hi>Maries</hi> reigne, is not yet impeached.</p>
            <p>There is yet one other Statute of later time, in which mention is made of Impoſitions, and that is, 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">14. H. 8. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 4. The words are, <hi>Every Subject borne in England, and ſworne to be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of other Princes, as long as they ſhall ſo abide Subjects to the other Princes, ſhal pay ſuch Cuſtoms, Subſidies, Tolls, and other Impoſitions, within this realme, as Strangers doe.</hi> I hold that this word <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> in this place is uſed as a generall to all the particulars before mentioned, and no otherwiſe, and is no more in effect then <hi>charges,</hi> a thing uſuall in Statutes of this nature, to adde generall words for the more ſecuritie, which I collect by the word <hi>(other)</hi> going next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, For to what end ſhould it be ſaid, <hi>no (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) Impoſitions,</hi> if thoſe particulars firſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, were not contained within that generall word <hi>of Impoſitions.</hi> This word <hi>(other)</hi> is a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and muſt needs be anſwered with words going before, when there are no other words following.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:157030:44"/>
            <p> Beſides, it is common in the Statutes and Records of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>No Impoſition upon woolls ſhall be laid, but in Parliament,</hi> By which it appears, that a charge laid by Parliament, may be called an Impoſition, which is very evident by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made not above 28. yeeres before this, I meane the Statute of 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">7 H 7. 7.</note> which I ſpake of even now, where a charge of Eighteen Shillings upon a Butt of Malmſey, laid by that Act of Parliament, is called an <hi>Impoſition;</hi> And as I have ſhewed you, the word <hi>Impoſition</hi> hath been applyed to all theſe ſeverall Inventions, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">The ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the words <hi>Maltolt,</hi> and <hi>Impoſition,</hi> or <hi>Impoſt.</hi>
               </note> for the charging of Merchandizes, Nay, the word <hi>Maltolt,</hi> which is Engliſhed by <hi>Raſtall, an evill Toll</hi> (as indeed it ſignifies) and in that reſpect, is of a farre harder ſenſe then the word <hi>Impoſition</hi>) is uſed indifferently for a <hi>charge</hi> ſet by Parliament, or a charge ſet by the Kings abſolute power upon Merchandiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Impoſitio</hi> derived from the verbe <hi>imponere,</hi> is no other then the Act of laying on, or impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and therefore in my opinion, Impoſitions are more properly by the Merchants called <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts</hi> which ſignifieth the things Impoſed. But I ſhall not need any further to enforce this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering it hath ſo liberally been confeſſed by the Kings Counſell,<note place="margin">No Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on laid from <hi>Ed.</hi> the Thirds time, till Q. <hi>Maries.</hi>
               </note> that there is no Record or Statute from <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. till Queen <hi>Maries</hi> reigne, that giveth any aſſurance that <hi>impoſitions,</hi> or ſo much as any one Impoſition was laid, during all that ſpace of above 170. yeers, only it behoves
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:157030:44"/> me for further opening the truth, to teſtifie, that being one of thoſe that were by you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to make ſearch in the ancient cuſtome Books of thoſe times, remaining in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, together with ſome of the beſt experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Merchants of this houſe, ſome of which had ſate at the receipt of Cuſtome, wee had many meetings, and ſpent many whole dayes in turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the old Cuſtome books, and as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as we could, did ſurvey ſome books of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very age and time; But after all our ſearch end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, could not finde any one Impoſition from the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. till Queen <hi>Maries</hi> reigne, to have been received by any Cuſtomer or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector. And if you pleaſe to give me leave to remember to you the paſſages of thoſe times, you cannot but marvell, that none of all thoſe Princes ſhould ſo much as attempt to trie the ſtrength of this ſo beneficiall a Prerogative, ſo much practiſed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and when you have heard their occaſions, and compared their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actions,<note place="margin">What great oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions all the Kings from <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. till Q. <hi>Ma.</hi> had to lay Impoſitions, and yet did it not.</note> with their forbearance in this kinde, you will, I think, conclude, and ſay in your hearts, that ſurely none of all thoſe Kings had ſo much as any imagination, that any ſuch Prerogative belonged unto them, as to raiſe money at their pleaſure, by laying a charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on merchandizes, to be exported or imported without aſſent in Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, being the Grand-childe and next Succeſſor of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Rich. 2.</note> (in whoſe times im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:157030:45"/> of all ſorts did ſo much rage) had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſſe occaſion then his Predeceſſor had: For firſt, he had little treaſure left him, and he was no ſooner in his Throne, but news was brought that the <hi>French</hi> had invaded the Realme, they had burned <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Haſtings</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> they had taken, and poſſeſſed the <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> they had beſieged <hi>Winchelſey:</hi> From the Northern parts, That the <hi>Scots</hi> had burned <hi>Roxborough,</hi> and were ready to overrunne all the North parts of <hi>England.</hi> Being thus beſet with warre on all ſides, doth his Counſell (which in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood, had moſt of them been of Counſell to his Grandfather) adviſe him to raiſe money by impoſitions, as his Grandfather had done (for this courſe of raiſing money by way of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, was yet freſh in all their memories?) they do not, but he taketh the ordinary courſe, by calling a Parliament, which for mainteinance of his charge in the war, the ſecond yeer of his reign, granteth him a Fifteenth; he calleth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parliam. and hath another Fifteenth gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Fourth yeere of his reigne, the warres increaſing, his neceſſities were ſuch, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Parliament, as they granted him a moſt unuſuall Taxe throughout the whole Kingdome, upon every Eccleſiaſticall perſon, one and other, Sixe ſhillings Eight pence, upon every other man or woman within the Realm, Foure pence, which when it came to be levied, cauſed (though cauſeleſly, becauſe it was legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:157030:45"/> granted) that notorious Rebellion of which <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> was the Captaine. This Taxe as it was levied not without that great Rebellion, ſo queſtionleſſe was it unwillingly yeelded to in Parliament; and yet becauſe there was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe thought lawfull for the raiſing of treaſure upon the Subjects goods, then by their own aſſent in Parliament, onely that courſe was thought fit to be practiſed, which was ſuch as ought to be obeyed.</p>
            <p>From the 5. to the 18. yeere of his Reigne, he obtained every other yeer one aide or other in Parliament; ſometimes a taxe, ſometimes a Fifteenth, ſometimes a Subſidie of Tonnage &amp; Poundage: In the eighteenth yeer, he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to go in perſon into <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſettle the ſtate of that Country then in Rebelion: all theſe troubles he had from abroade beſides thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Rebellions here at home, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards caſt him out of his Seat; yet did he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for all this attempt to lay impoſitions, though he wanted not about him, to put him in minde of his abſolute power: For <hi>Edward Strafford,</hi> Biſhop of Exeter, Lord Chancellor of England, in a Sermon made to the Parliament held, <hi>anno</hi> 21. as our Chronicles report, did publiquely maintaint that the King was not bound by any Law; but was of himſelf abſolute &amp; above Law, and that to controle any of his actions was an offence worthy of Death, at which Parliament all that were preſent came
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:157030:46"/> armed for fear of the King; and the Parliament Houſe it ſelfe was beſet with 4000. Archers by his appointment. I will ſpeak no more of him then this; though he were a King of a weak ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yet did he not ſpare to practiſe upon his people the moſt grievous things that were; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he ſo farre diſcontented them that they depoſed him by common conſent in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the onely deſperate example of that kinde, that our Hiſtories doe afford, or I hope ever ſhall.</p>
            <p>His ſucceſſor <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">Hen. 4.</note> in reſpect he held the Crown by ſo weak a title, had cauſe to give the people all the content he could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and yet he was ſo oppreſſed with warrs on all ſides, from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by continuall and dangerous invaſions made by the <hi>Welſh,</hi> as without the aide of his people for the ſupply of his treaſure; it had not been poſſible for him to have held his Crown on his head, and therefore he preſſed his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo farre, that in a Parliament held the fifth yeere of his reigne, they yeelded to him ſo great and ſo unaccuſtomed a tax, as that the grantors thereof, as our Chroniclers ſay, tooke ſpeciall order that no memory thereof ſhould remaine of record onely to avoide the preſident; and yet the very next yeere following, his wants were againe grown ſo great as his Subjects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſembled in Parliament to give him fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ayde, did reſolve that there was no other
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:157030:46"/> way to ſupply his want, then to take from the Clergie their temporall Lands and goods, and to give them all to the King, which being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the Clergie, a reſumption of all the guifts of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. was propounded: at laſt (after they had ſate a whole yeere) they gave him two Fifteenths; at this time, moſt of his Counſell, and the great Officers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were Spirituall men; had they not now, (if ever) a juſt occaſion given them to have put the King in minde of his Prerogative of laying impoſitions, not onely to the intent to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted him from the harkning to that deſperate motion that had been made againſt them to all their utter undoings, but were they not alſo bound in duty and conſcience, in this time of ſo great neceſſitie (ſeeing the Parliament knew not otherwiſe how to ſupplie the Kings wants) to have adviſed him to have made uſe of his lawfull right of impoſing, by which means, he might, without troubling the Parliament, quickly have raiſed great ſummes of money: certainly it was not becauſe they were ignorant of any ſuch practiſe in former times, For none of them that were then of the Counſell to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Fourth, but they lived in <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. time, and moſt of them doubtleſſe, were in <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. time men of age and diſcretion; But in all likelyhood as they knew that <hi>Edward</hi> the Third did lay im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, ſo likewiſe they knew that impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had been from time to time, in thoſe daies
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:157030:47"/> condemned as unlawfull, and were become hatefull to the people, and onely for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they did forbeare to adviſe the King to take that courſe, though the neceſſitie were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great.</p>
            <p>Another Prerogative, as much concerning the intereſt of the Subject, as this of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, namely the abaſing of Coyne, this King made no ſcruple at all to put in practiſe, becauſe he held it to be lawfull.</p>
            <p>His Sonne, and next Succeſſor, <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. who by his many victories over the <hi>French,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hen. 5.</note> and his noble diſpoſition and behaviour towards his people, was ſo farre beloved of them, as never was King of this Realme more, though the Kingdome were now, by one degree of diſcent, more firmely ſetled upon him then it was on his Father (who uſurped it) though alſo his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of treaſure, by reaſon of that great warre in <hi>France,</hi> were as much, as any king's of <hi>England</hi> ever were, though he had troubles alſo from his Neighbours the <hi>Scots,</hi> and within his owne Realme, by Rebellions: and laſtly, though he ſpared not for ſupplie of treaſure, to ſuppreſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a 100. Priories of Aliens; yet neither out of the ſtrength of his love with the people, nor in his extreame neceſſity, by reaſon of theſe honorable warres in <hi>France,</hi> for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of which, the people would willingly have undergone any burden which he would have laid upon them, eſpecially after the victory
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:157030:47"/> at <hi>Agencourt,</hi> did he ever ſo much as attempt the laying of Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>His Succeſſor <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">Hen. 6.</note> (though indeed of a meek ſpirit) yet he was ſo followed with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles within the Realme, and from abroad, that he was inforced to crave ſuch an extraordinary aide of his Subjects in Parliament, as the levie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof was the cauſe of that famous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>Jack Cade</hi> in his time. Beſides, in the 18 yeer of his Reign, for the eaſe of his charge and ſupply of his wants, all Grants by him made of any Lands, Rents, Annuities, or Fees what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſince the firſt day of his Reigne, were reſumed: and this is never yeelded to, but in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of extreame neceſſity. As for Impoſitions, notwithſtanding his great wants, he thought not of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Edw. 4.</note> that ſucceeded him, was no leſſe free from troubles; for he was (as you know) driven to forſake his Kingdome, and to live for a while like a baniſhed man with the Duke of <hi>Burgundy;</hi> He was alſo inforced in the 5 yeer of his Reign to make a Reſumption; and the ſame yeer to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe his Coyne: And <hi>Comines</hi> obſerveth of him, that he obteined a Subſidie of his Subjects in Parliament, upon condition that he ſhould himſelfe in perſon undertake the war in France; and, that only to get the Subſidie, he paſſed the Seas into France, but preſently returned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any thing. What ſhould ſuch ſhifts as theſe have needed, if he might (without being
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:157030:48"/> beholding to his Subjects) lawfully, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controll have raiſed Treaſure by laying of Impoſitions? It is well worth the remembring, that which the ſame <hi>Comines</hi> (ſpeaking in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the frame of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth) ſaith; <hi>That this State is happy, in that the people cannot be compelled by the King to ſuſtein any publique charge, except it be by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed from <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. to <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">Hen. 7.</note> (omitting <hi>Ed.</hi> 5. and <hi>Ric.</hi> 3. becauſe of the ſhortnes of their Reignes.) <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>H.</hi> 7. had a Subſidy of Tunnage and Poundage granted to him for his life, as may appear by the Parl. Roll 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. which appeares no where in our printed books.</note> had indeed a more peaceable time than any of his Predeceſſors; and yet he was not altogether free from troubles both within the Realme, and from abroad: But his naturall inclination was rather to embrace Peace; he was ſo provident and politique in the gathering and ſtoring up of Treaſure, as never any Prince of this Realme was therein to be compared to him: He did himſelfe take the accounts of his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, (which I have ſeen under his own hand:) He had for his Aſſiſtants about him, <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley,</hi> men learned in the Lawes, and by all probability, very canning in all the profitable points of the Prerogative; men that that inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or ſtudied little elſe than the advancing of their Maſters profit; men even till this day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous for their wicked counſell, in perſwading that good King to lay ſuch heavy Exactions and Burdens upon his people, as he did: If theſe men who in all likelihood ſhould have beſt knowne
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:157030:48"/> the Kings right (eſpecially in ſo high a point of profit) had but had the leaſt notice of ſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table a Prerogative as this, would they not have been at ſtrife which of them ſhould firſt have put the king in minde thereof? Or if they had held it queſtionable, would they not have put it to ſome triall? Certainly there can be no cauſe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that ſhould make them thus to forbeare, but either they were utterly ignorant of any ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, or, that knowing ſuch a thing to be clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by ſome of the ancient kings (eſpecially by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.) they knew likewiſe that it was in the ſame times continually complained of in Parliament, and alwayes condemned; and that there were acts of Parliament directly againſt it, and this is more probably to bee conceived of them being men of ſuch ſearching ſpirits, and ſo well ſtudied in point of Prerogative, then that they were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the practiſe of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. conſidering alſo that they were nerer to thoſe times by 120 yeers then wee are.</p>
            <p>But that which moſt of all moves me herein is that there was in <hi>H.</hi> 7. time ſuch an occaſion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered of making uſe of this Prerogative, as there could not poſſibly happen any other that might better have juſtified the laying of Impoſitions; which was this: The Venetians, to the intent to drive our Merchants from fetching ſweet wines at <hi>Candy,</hi> that they might the better imploy their owne ſhips and Merchants, did impoſe upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very But of Malmeſey brought thence by En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:157030:49"/> Merchants foure Duccats, by which means the Engliſh wholly loſt that Trade, and the Venetians made the whole profit thereof: This miſchiefe was no other way better to be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, than by impoſing the like, or a greater charge upon Merchants of <hi>Candy</hi> bringing Malm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey into England; that ſo they of <hi>Candy</hi> not being able to afford them better cheape than the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, the Engliſh might ſtill fetch them from <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> as they had wont to doe. I ſay, there could not poſſibly be a more juſtifiable occaſion of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Impoſitions, than this was: And did this king (ſo carefull in other things of preſerving his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and moſt of all in matters that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his profit) take hold of this occaſion to lay an Impoſition by his abſolute power? Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though he ſaw it convenient, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner neceſſary, yet he conceived it to be unlawfull ſo to doe; and therefore did it not by his abſolute power, but by aſſent of Parliament, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the Statute of 7 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. printed; where, in the preamble of the Act, you ſhall ſee the occaſion of the making of the Act to be as I have opened it unto you: and you may perceive by the body of the Act, that for the counterpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the impoſition of foure Duccats laid by the Venetians upon our Merchants, there was impoſed 18<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. for a But of Malmeſey, upon their Merchants bringing it hither, to laſt as long as the impoſition of foure Duccats (which, as appeares by the Act, came but to 18<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.of our mony) ſhould
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:157030:49"/> endure. It is not probable that this king, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his other actions, would have ſuffered this to have been done by Parliament, if he had thought he might have lawfully done it by his abſolute power? And therfore it cannot almoſt be gaine-ſaid, that in theſe times this pretended Prerogative of laying Impoſitions without aſſent of Parliament was held to be againſt Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. his ſonne and ſucceſſor,<note place="margin">Hen. 8.</note> was ſo farre from the diſpoſition of his father, in this point of thrift and providence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. had a Subſidie of Tunnage and Poundage gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for his life, the firſt yeare of his Reign, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the Parl. Roll.</note> as there was not in the whol ranke of our kings any one like to him, for exceſſive prodigality; the great riches ſtored up by his father, with ſo much care, and left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, hee ſo ſodainly conſumed in Triumphs, Maskes, Mummeries, Banquets, pompous and braving Warres, as was that of <hi>Turwin</hi> and <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> and in the ſatsfying of his luſt, as he was out of very neceſſity enforced to crave moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable aids of his Subjects in Parliament, ſuch as never before had been granted, which through very dread and feare were yeelded to him; yet not ſo ſatisfied, that no meanes for the rayſing of money might bee neglected or unattempted, in the 15 yeere of his Reigne, by the councell of that proud Prelate Cardinall <hi>Woolſey,</hi> hee ſpared not to ſend out Commiſſions into every ſhire throughout the whole Realme, with privy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to the Commiſſioners, how they ſhould with moſt advantage behave themſelves, in perſwading the people to contribute to the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:157030:50"/> king the ſixt part of their whole eſtates, to bee paid preſently, either in money or plate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon followed extreme curſing, weeping and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation againſt the king and his councell, and the people were in point to rebell had not the king ſtayed the proceedings of the commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by his Letters. Finding that this way would not ſerve his turne, hee demanded a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence, which not anſwering his expectation, hee did the ſame yeere raiſe unto himſelfe a great deale of treaſure by abaſing his gold.</p>
            <p>Such things as theſe Princes never put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe but when all other meanes faile them, and yet hee went many degrees beyond this: For, in the 27. yeer of his reigne he ſuppreſſed above 370 Religious houſes, the yeerly value of whoſe revenues I have read to be no leſſe than 32000<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. <hi>per annum</hi> in thoſe dayes: and that of their goods (ſold at very low priſes) he made above 100000<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. in preſent money. About 4. yeares after he diſſolved all the Monaſteries, Abbeies, Priories, Nunneries, and all other Religious hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of what kinde ſoever throughout England. By which meanes, and by the ſale of their goods he gathered ſuch a maſſe of Treaſure, as it might have been imagined that never any king of this Realme ſhould have needed to have ſought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe at his Subjects hands: Yet he himſelfe, no longer than within 3. yeeres after following, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and obteined (as may appeare by the Statutes of that time) an exceſſive great Ayde by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:157030:50"/> and yet the yeere following hee did alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe his coyne, more then halfe in halfe, ſuch an abaſement as never before or ſince was heard of, and could not but bee very grievous to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but becauſe perhaps they held it lawfull ſo to doe, they made no pubilque complaint there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and it is worth the obſerving, That though this Prerogative of abaſing Coyne be a thing which trencheth as deepely into the privat inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Subject as the laying of Impoſitions; for, by this meanes a man, that this day is worth in revenues a hundred pounds <hi>per an.</hi> hee ſhall to morrow, if the king be ſo pleaſed, be worth but fifty or forty, or leſſe, in reall value; and though alſo the practiſe of this Prerogative hath not been forborne by any of the kings of this Realm, and that ſome of them have uſed it very immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, yet cannot there be found any one pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique complaint, that ever I have met withall, upon Record againſt it, as from time to time there have beene many againſt Impoſitions, which argues that the Subject did make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between theſe two Prerogatives; this, of laying Impoſitions; and that, of abaſing coyne; thinking the one lawfull and the other not. But to conclude my obſervations upon the actions of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. The next yeere after this unconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abaſement of his money, hee craved a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence. The yeere following he tooke the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of all the Chantries, Colledges and free Chappels, &amp;c. during his life, which ended the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:157030:51"/> next yeere: Can any man imagine that during this kings Reigne it was held lawfull (or any ſuch thing ſo much as dreamed of) to rayſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by laying Impoſitions; I will enforce it no farther, but leave it to the judgement of any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man that ſhall conſider theſe things which I have remembred, whether or no it bee likely.</p>
            <p>Out of the time of his Sonne and Succeſſor <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">Edw. 6.</note> I can obſerve little, becauſe of the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Reigne; but methinkes, if his Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors had imagined that any ſuch Prerogative had been due unto him, they ſhould not in honor have forborn the practiſe thereof for the ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Kings great neceſſities, and in ſtead thereof have craved of the Subjects that unacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed and unreaſonable Subſidy, granted <hi>an.</hi> 2. of a certaine ſum of money upon every ſheep and every Cloth within the Realme, for 3. yeeres; which afterwards for the unreaſonablenes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was releaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have now gone through in ſuch ſort as you have heard,<note place="margin">A Corolary or connexion of all the times before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</note> the times of all the Kings from</hi> Ed. 3. <hi>till</hi> Q. Maries <hi>Reigne: during which time what can there be more imagined, that might poſſibly have happened to have awakened Impoſitions, if they had not been more than aſleepe? Neither the neceſsity of juſt and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable warre, nor the ſubtleties and curioſitie of Peace, nor the prodigality of ſome of theſe Kings for the better ſatisfying of their pleaſures, nor the covetouſneſſe of others, nor the ſoftneſſe of ſome of their diſpoſitions,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:157030:51"/> nor the nonage of others apt to be abuſed by evill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, nor the dreadfull and fearefull awe in which ſome of them held their Subjects, nor the aſſurance of the peoples extraordinary affection, which might have emboldened ſome others; nor the evill conſcience of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers, nor any other motive whatſoever which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened during this long time, could revive them; untill</hi> Q. Mary <hi>did at laſt raiſe them out of the grave, after they had been ſo many yeeres dead and rotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Impoſition that ſhe layd,<note place="margin">Qu. Mary.</note> was that upon Cloth, continued till this day, which grew upon a ſpeciall reaſon, as may appeare by the printed booke of the rates of her Cuſtomes and Subſidies; in the end whereof you ſhall finde a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration expreſſing the loſſe ſuſteined by reaſon of the difference between the Cuſtomes and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies of Wool and cloth, by which it appeares that a ſack of Wool yeelded in cuſtome ſix ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings eight pence, and in Subſidie thirty three ſhillings foure pence; that the cuſtom upon a ſhort cloth was fourteene-pence, and that a ſack of Wool did commonly make foure ſhort clothes, the cuſtome of which was foure ſhillings eight pence; ſo that the custome of Wool made into cloth, was leſſe then the Cuſtome and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie of ſo much Wool not cloathed; In every ſack in ſhort clothes thirty five ſhillings foure-pence: which difference was reduced to an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by rating upon every ſhort cloth ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: After this declaration made of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and of the rate which reduced both to an
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:157030:52"/> equality, follow theſe words; Which diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence conſidered, and the great loſſe ſuſteined by Us in the ſame, by reaſon that cloathing is much increaſed, It is thought convenient by Us, with the advice of our Councell, towards the reliefe of the loſſe, for to aſſeſſe upon the Clothes carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, by way of Merchandize, ſome larger rate then heretofore hath been uſed, and though it were reaſon to appoint ſuch a rate as might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence the full of the loſſe ſuſteined, yet upon divers conſiderations, at this time, Us and Our Councell moving, Wee are pleaſed only to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe upon every ſhort-cloath, by the name of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, ſix ſhillings eight pence, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I thought good to open this at large unto you that you might ſee upon what ſpeciall reaſon of equity this Impoſition was grounded, and how it differeth from ours: And it is worthy the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, how the Queene commandeth this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Cuſtome to be yeelded unto her, not as an Impoſition, or by the name of Impoſt, but by the name of Cuſtome, becauſe it cometh in lieu of the ancient Cuſtome upon Wooll, which is the reaſon that at this day it is deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and paid by that name; whereas no other new raiſed duty hath that priviledge; but they are either called Subſidie of Tonnage or Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, if they be raiſed by act of Parliament; or Impoſt, if by the Kings abſolute power.</p>
            <p>The name of Cuſtome was anciently given to none but to Wools, Wool-fells, and Leather;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:157030:52"/> and upon this occaſion, to Cloth alſo.</p>
            <p>This Impoſition, though grounded upon ſuch equity as you have heard, yet in <hi>Dyer,</hi> 1 <hi>Eliz. fo.</hi> 165. <hi>a.</hi> &amp; <hi>b.</hi> it was, as appeares by my L. <hi>Dyer,</hi> complayned of by the Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> with great exclamation (which are his words) and ſuit to the Queen to be unburdoned of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not granted in Parliament, but aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of her abſolute power: whereupon there were divers aſſemblies and conferences of the Juſtices and others,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plowdens</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt it, in M. <hi>Tates</hi> hand.</note> but their reſolution is no where to be found, at leaſt by Us; It is very probable that if they had given judgement for the Queen, it would not have beene kept cloſe, but howſoever the profit was too great to be taken from the Crowne and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it continues till this day.</p>
            <p>Howſoever the reaſon in equity in the laying this Impoſition upon Cloth may ſeeme to bee ſound unto ſome men, and ſo to allow of this Impoſition as differing from ours, yet for my part, I hold it not ſo, when I conſider what courſe was taken by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. upon the ſame occaſion, <hi>an.</hi> 11. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. &amp; 2. It was enacted, that no wooll ſhould be caried out of <hi>England,</hi> but by the Kings licence; and that no man ſhould weare Cloth, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſuch as ſhould be made in <hi>England:</hi> this Law tooke ſuch effect, as within ten yeeres the greateſt part of the Wooll in <hi>England</hi> was made into Cloth; and it became to be tranſported in ſuch abundance, by reaſon that there was no Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:157030:53"/> at all due upon Cloth, and the Cuſtome and Subſidie upon Wools was very high, that in the 21 yeere, the King finding his Cuſtome of Wools ſo much decreaſed, doth ſeeke to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it, not by impoſing a new charge upon Cloth by his abſolute power, as Qu. <hi>Mary</hi> did, but did it by aſſent of his Subjects in full Parliament, as I collect partly by my L. <hi>Dyer</hi> in the place laſt mentioned, but more fully by a recitall in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord amongſt us, of 24. <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>ro.</hi> 13. <hi>orig de Scaccar.</hi> to this effect: <hi>That whereas the Cuſtomes and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies due and granted upon Wools are much decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe a great part of the Wooll of England is made into Cloth, for which no Cuſtome is due; and whereas in conſideration thereof, at our Councel held the 21 yeere of our Reigne, by the common aſſent of the Prelates, Earles and Barons, and others, it was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and accorded, that</hi> 14<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>by Denizens, and</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>by Strangers ſhould be paid for every cloth of Aſſiſe, &amp;c. made of Engliſh wooll, and tranſported; upon paine of forfeiture of the Clothes:</hi> And ſo followeth an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given to collect the ſame.</p>
            <p>The next Impoſition laid by Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> was forty ſhillings upon a Tun of French wines, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the 5 yeere of her Reigne: at which time there was firſt a Proclamation made, that no wines at all ſhould be brought from France, being then in enmity with England, upon paine of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of the Wines; (which, by the way, is a ſtrange clauſe in a proclamation.) Immediately after this reſtraint there was an order made by the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:157030:53"/> 
               <hi>Qu.</hi> and her privy Counſell, that ſuch as would might bring in French wines, notwithſtanding the Proclamation, paying forty ſhillings upon every Tun by the name of Impoſt, as doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by Record in the Rolls of Eaſter Terme, 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the office of the <hi>K.</hi> Remembrancer of the Exchequer, in the caſe of one <hi>Germane Ciol,</hi>
               <note place="margin">German Ciols <hi>caſe.</hi>
               </note> againſt whom an Information was exhibited for not paying the ſaid Impoſition: Whereunto, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it by way of Traverſe, that there is any Law of the Land by which he may be charged with Impoſt, he pleads a licence made unto him, <hi>an.</hi> 1. &amp; 2. <hi>Ph. &amp; Mar.</hi> to import a certaine number of Tunnes of Wine within a certain time, any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint then made, or afterwards to be made to the contrary, notwithſtanding; Provided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that the Cuſtome, Subſidie, and other duties due and accuſtomed to be paid to the King and Queen, were duly ſatisfied; He ſhewes, that for all Wines brought in by him during the life of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> he paid the Subſidie of Tonnage, <hi>viz.</hi> three ſhillings for every Tun, which was all that was due and accuſtomed to be paid: Upon this plea a demurrer was joyned, and judgement given thereupon againſt the Queen; This Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath been enforced in the maintenance of Impoſitions: Whether or no it make not rather againſt them, I leave to your cenſures.</p>
            <p>Neere about the ſame time there were Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions laid alſo by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> upon all French commodities whatſoever to be imported, as may
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:157030:54"/> appeare by the Port-bookes of thoſe times in the Exchequer; which Impoſitions were received to the uſe of Queene <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the beginning of the 1 yeere of her Reign, but ere the yeer ended they were all taken away, as may appeare by the ſame Port-bookes; which in my opinion is a great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that they were not then held lawfull: For, Princes doe not ſo eaſily give over their hold in matters of profit, if they be any way able to maintain it. What hath hitherto upheld the Impoſition upon Wines, I know not, except it be the great profit that comes by it to the Crown, and becauſe there was never any late Judgement given directly againſt Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>You have hitherto heard what reaſon and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect proofe I have uſed,<note place="margin">Admitting the king had po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Lawe to lay Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet hee is barred by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</note> to maintaine, that by the Common Law the King cannot at his will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his Cuſtome by way of Impoſition: You have, ſecondly, heard what the practiſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages hath been in this kinde, till this day; from which I have alſo drawn reaſons of Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that prove the Common-Law ſo to be. But now, admitting that by the Common-Law it had been cleere and without queſtion, that the King might at his will have laid Impoſitions and that alſo the ſame could have been cleerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the practiſe of the ancient Kings, yet I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that ſo ſtands the Law of England at this day (by reaſon of Statutes directly in the point) as the Kings power, if ever he had any to impoſe, is not onely limited, but utterly taken away, as I
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:157030:54"/> hope I ſhall be able evidently to prove, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any objection that hath been made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the interpretation of the Statutes to this ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt Statute is in <hi>Magna Charta, cap.</hi> 30.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magna Charta cap.</hi> 30. Enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jections made againſt it, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> The words are; <hi>All Merchants, if they were not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly prohibited before, ſhall have their ſafe and ſure conducts, to enter and depart, to goe and tarrie in the Realme as well by Land as by water, to buy and ſell without any evill tolls, by the old and rightfull Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes (except in the time of Warre.) And if they be of the Land making warre againſt us, and be found in our Realme at the beginning of the warre, they ſhall be attached without harme of body, or goods, untill it be knowne to us, or our Juſtices, how our Merchants be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated there in the Land making war againſt us, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Statute of which this is a branch, is the moſt ancient Statute-Law we have, wonne and ſealed with the blood of our Anceſtors; ſo reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in former times, that it hath been by Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament provided, that Tranſcripts thereof ſhould be ſent to all the Cathedrall Churches of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, there to remaine; that it ſhould be twice e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yeere publikely read before the people; that likewiſe twice every yeere there ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication ſolemnly denounced to the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers thereof; that all Statutes and all Judgements given againſt it ſhal be held as void; that it ſhould be received and allowed as the Common-Law, by all ſuch as have the adminiſtration of Juſtice;<note place="margin">25 <hi>E.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 1.2.3.4.</note> and it hath been no leſſe than 29 times ſolemnly
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:157030:55"/> confirmed in Parliament: I will therefore with ſo much the more care endeavor to free this Law from all the objections that have been made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>The firſt objection doth tend to the diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the extent of this Statute,<note place="margin">The firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that it extendeth only to Merchant-ſtrangers, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> as touching the perſons whom it may concerne; for it hath been collected out of the latter words of the Statute, that it ſhould extend onely to Merchants-Aliens, and not to Denizens.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is improbable that the makers of the Law ſhould be more carefull to provide for the indempnity of Merchant-ſtrangers than of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; except perhaps they might imagine that Engliſh Merchants were already ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for by the Common-Law: If that were their reaſon (as there could be no other that I can imagine) it doth as much maintaine my opinion, as if they had been conteined within the Statute.</p>
            <p>Again, the words are generall: All Merchants; and,<hi>Qui omnes dixerit, nullos excipit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the Statute is a beneficiall Law; in which caſe particular and ſpeciall words doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes admit a generall extent: And therefore, to reſtraine generall words, as the Objectors would, is againſt all reaſon, and rule of Law. As for the latter words, 'tis true, they doe indeed extend onely to Merchant-ſtrangers; but the ſenſe of the firſt ſentence is perfect without this: and as long as no abſurdity nor contradiction doth follow by interpreting the firſt words to extend to all
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:157030:55"/> Merchants in generall, and the latter onely to Merchant-ſtrangers, the moſt ample and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall conſtruction is ever the beſt, as in all other Statutes of this nature.</p>
            <p>But this objection is, in my opinion, cleerly removed by 2. Statutes made by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this very clauſe: The firſt is, 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. the words are, <hi>All merchants, Strangers and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies may goe and come with their merchandizes into England, after the tenure of the Great Charter.</hi> I take it, that <hi>Privies</hi> in this place, being the very word that is found in the Originall, which is in French, ought to be underſtood Denizens; for, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I ſuppoſe it would have been joyned to the word [Strangers] by a conjunction disjunctive, which is uſuall where the words are of one ſenſe; and not by a copulative, as here it is. Beſides, I take the word [Privy] to be derived from the Latine, <hi>Privatus,</hi> which ſignifieth a particular property; as <hi>res privata,</hi> a mans owne private e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: ſo, <hi>mercatores privati,</hi> our own Merchants. That Merchant-ſtrangers ſhould be firſt named, is common in Statutes and Records.</p>
            <p>The next Statute explaining this of <hi>magna Charta,</hi> is, 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. The words are, <hi>VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is conteined in the Great Charter, that</hi> all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants <hi>ſhall have ſafe conduct, &amp;c. VVee grant that</hi> all Merchants, <hi>Denizens and Forreins, may freely paſſe, &amp;c.</hi> which I take to be no other than a meere declaration of <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Objection made againſt this
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:157030:56"/> branch of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond Objection. That <hi>Magna Charta</hi> cap 30. was made only againſt Taxes within the Land, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> is, That the meaning thereof was to ſecure the Merchants, not from a new increaſe of Cuſtome to be impoſed by the King, to be paid at their entrance or going out of the Ports, ſuch as our Impoſitions are; but from certaine petty exactions, as Tolls and ſuch like, which were then uſually demanded of them within the Land, by the Townes through which they were to paſſe and where they ſold their Merchandize; for the farther remedy of which there were afterwards divers Statutes made which doe evidently manifeſt that ſuch was the miſchiefe, and they doe the rather make this collection becauſe of the words, <hi>buy and ſell without evill tolts;</hi> For, ſay they, Impoſitions are not paid upon the buying and ſelling of Merchandize, but when they are to ſhip or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: they take hold of the word Toll, which properly is an exaction for paſſage within the land, or for ſale in markets or faires. Theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, notwithſtanding I hold it ſomewhat cleere that the meaning of this Statute was principally to ſecure Merchants touching Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. My firſt argument is drawn <hi>ab Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate,</hi> from the authority of the wiſeſt and moſt ſage men in greateſt places and offices within this kingdom, in the times wherein they lived, and who alſo could ſo much the better judge of the true meaneng of this Statute in that they lived ſo neere the time of the making thereof, even in the beginning of the reigne of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:157030:56"/> the next King (ſave one) to him that made this Statute: I meane thoſe who made the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. heretofore divers times men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by me, who in alledging their reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> doe amongſt other things ſay that the ſame was made againſt <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta;</hi> What was the cauſe of the griefe conceived againſt <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> other then the Impoſitions by colour thereof, laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forraine commodities; It appeares by the Ordinance, that was the onely cauſe: if then <hi>Charta Mercatoria</hi> were by them adjudged to be againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> only becauſe by colour thereof, new Impoſitions were raiſed, without aſſent of Parliament, it is evident, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to be made againſt impoſitions; if they had thought it to have extended onely to petty tolls and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions within the land, as is objected, then could it not have extended to <hi>Charta Mercatoria.</hi> As for the words <hi>Buy</hi> and <hi>Sell,</hi> without any manner of evill Toll; I denie not but the words may perhaps have that ſenſe, which hath been col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of them, <hi>viz.</hi> that in buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, they ſhould be free alſo from unjuſt exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within the land. But I ſay further, that theſe words, without any manner of Evill Toll, by the old and rightfull Cuſtomes, do extend not onely to the next precedent words (Buy and ſell) but alſo to the former words, Enter and returne, and more principally to them then to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:157030:57"/> any other; For to have provided that they ſhould be free from thoſe petty exactions of tolls in Markets, and for paſſing through Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Townes, and to leave them ſubject to Impoſitions, to be laid on at the Kings pleaſure, had been but a ſlender ſecuritie. This expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mine is confirmed by a Record here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, of 16. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. no longer then ſeven yeers after the making of this Statute. By which it appeares, that the King commanded his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, at the <hi>Ports, to ſignifie to all Merchants, that they might with ſafetie enter into his kingdom, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rightfull and ancient cuſtomes, Nec time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſibi de Maletoltis quas faciet Rex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the word Toll,<note place="margin">Derivation of the word <hi>Toll.</hi>
               </note> which they ſay is to be underſtood of Toles for paſſages, and for buying and ſelling in Faires and Markets, it behoves me to ſay ſomething of the derivation thereof, the rather becauſe it is very often uſed in our ancient Statutes and Records in the ſame ſenſe, as it is in this place; and by the derivation thereof the naturall and true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the word ſhall be beſt underſtood; I hold it therefore to be derived from the Latine word <hi>Teolonium,</hi> which ſignifies cuſtome, by cutting off the latter part of the word, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining onely the firſt part <hi>Teol,</hi> by contraction <hi>Toll,</hi> of which manner of derivation, there are infinite examples in our language, the Latine <hi>Teolonium</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi> in his <hi>Lexicon Juris Civilis)</hi> is derived from the Greek <hi>Telos,</hi> which
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:157030:57"/> ſignifies aſwell Cuſtom as it doth <hi>Finis:</hi> Hence it is that the Cuſtomers are called in Latine <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonarii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee that the genuine, and prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſignification of our word <hi>Toll,</hi> is no other then Cuſtome upon Merchandizes: from the word <hi>Toll</hi> are come thoſe two barbarours Latine words found in our Statutes, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, <hi>Toltum,</hi> which is the word uſed in the Record of 16 <hi>H.</hi> 6. but even now vouched by me; and <hi>Tolnetum,</hi> the Originall word in the Statute now in queſtion, which I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe is alſo in our Law Latine uſed by us for <hi>Toll</hi> in the Market, and <hi>Toll</hi> for paſſage, as may appear by the Regiſter, and the Book of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etries. But in this place, <hi>Malum tolnetum</hi> proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifies not a Toll in the common ſence, but an unlawfull charge laid by the King upon Merchandizes, as an increaſe of Cuſtome, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Primitive ſignification, which is evidently proved in that it is here oppoſed to old and rightfull Cuſtomes; <hi>ſine omnibus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Tolnetis per certas &amp; antiquas conſuetudines;</hi> wherfore it ought ſo to have been tranſlated, for ſo it ſignifies, without Impoſitions, by the old and rightfull Cuſtome: This expoſition and tranſlation is further warranted by the uſe of the word <hi>Maletolt,</hi> ſo often found in our anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Statutes &amp; Records, which without ſcruple is derived from the Latine, <hi>Malum Tolnetum,</hi> the very word of our Statute; I finde it diverſly
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:157030:58"/> written, <hi>Maletout, Maletolt, Maletot,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Maletent,</hi> but I never finde it any where uſed in any other ſence then for an Impoſition by way of increaſe of Cuſtome upon Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes: Sometimes indeed but that very rarely, It is taken in the beſt ſence for lawfull and rightfull Cuſtome, as the word Impoſition ſometimes is, but then commonly it is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with another word to free it from the worſt ſence, as <hi>Droiturel Maletout, &amp;c.</hi> That <hi>malis Tolnetis</hi> is in this place ought to be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Impoſitions, may be farther proved by that which I finde in a writer of the french Hiſtory, one <hi>Jean Serres,</hi> who ſaies, That in the time of <hi>Philip le Beau</hi> king of France, which was about the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. king of England, there were rebellions in France becauſe of Impoſitions laid by the K. which in thoſe days, they did, ſaith he, call <hi>Maletouts,</hi> the very word then anciently u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Engl. for Impoſitions, as may plentifully appeare by the Statutes and Records of <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Ed.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">The word Impoſition.</note> for the word <hi>Impoſition</hi> was not uſed in any French Record, Statute or other, for ought I have ſeene, till <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. I finde it once uſed in Latine, 12. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. in the Letter which King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third writ to the Archbiſhop, to excuſe him to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for laying Impoſitions, and as all that Letter throughout, is of an eloquent ſtile, ſo as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he was carefull to avoid alſo that barbarous word, <hi>Malum tolnetum,</hi> though common and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:157030:58"/> familiar, and in ſtead thereof, to uſe the pure Latine word <hi>Impoſitio. Sylvius</hi> writing upon <hi>Tullies</hi> Oration for <hi>Marcus Fonteius,</hi> where theſe words are uſed by <hi>Tully, Impoſuit vectigal,</hi> (ſaith) <hi>Ita uſitatum vulgo eſt ut</hi> vectigalia <hi>nova appellent Impoſitiones.</hi> The word <hi>Vectigal,</hi> in this place, though in a generall ſence it may be applyed to any revenew whatſoever, yet with the Civill Lawyers, it is by way of Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, commonly uſed for Cuſtom, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by <hi>Calvin</hi> in his <hi>Lexicon,</hi> Vectigal <hi>quod Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co vel Reipubl. portorii nomine pendintur, id eſt, pro mercibus quae invehuntur vel evehuntur,</hi> Sometimes they uſe to joyne with it for a more cleere diſtinction, the word <hi>Portorium,</hi> as a man would ſay, the revenue of the Ports, agreeable with which, upon ſome Records of <hi>Henry</hi> the Thirds time, I have found it to be called, <hi>Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Portuum.</hi> By this it is evident, that <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio</hi> in pure Latine, and Impoſition in Engliſh, is the ſame with <hi>Maletolt</hi> in French, and <hi>Malum tolnetum</hi> in our Law Latine; and they doe all ſignifie a new increaſe of Cuſtome, and not any thing elſe; Wherefore I conclude, that theſe words, <hi>ſine malis Tolnetis,</hi> in our preſent Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, are naturally and properly to be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and underſtood of <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> and ſo ought to have been tranſlated, and not as they are; and although the word <hi>Impoſition</hi> it ſelf, as alſo the word <hi>Maletout,</hi> and <hi>Malum tolnetum</hi> may be (as I have confeſſed) taken as well for a
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:157030:59"/> new increaſe of Cuſtome, by a lawfull means <hi>(viz.)</hi> by aſſent in Parliament: as for an increaſe of Cuſtome by the Kings abſolute power, which is unlawful, yet by the words that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately follow, it is evident that this Statute doth onely intend unlawfull impoſitions, that is, impoſitions laid by the Kings abſolute po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, without aſſent in Parliament, otherwiſe would they not have been oppoſed to due and rightfull cuſtomes, as by the words of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute they are.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there hath been ſome exception alſo taken to the expoſition of the word <hi>Cuſtom</hi> in that ſence in which I take it (that is) for cuſtome upon Merchandize, for that the word in the Originall is <hi>Conſuetudo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The word Cuſtom, <hi>Cuſtuma,</hi> and <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> expounded.</note> which ſignifies an uſage, and not <hi>Cuſtuma,</hi> which is the Latine word we now uſe for Cuſtome upon Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize; it behoves me therfore to ſay ſomething touching theſe words, <hi>Conſetudo,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtuma,</hi> for the cleering of this ſcruple. This word <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> in his firſt and proper ſignification, doth, I confeſſe, ſignifie an uſage, or practiſe of a thing time out of minde, but it is evident by the Records in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 3. and <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. this word in a more ſpeciall manner, was applied to all, or moſt of the duties belonging to the Crowne, by reaſon of Trade, As <hi>Conſuetudo aquae Thameſis, Conſuetudo piſcis venientis ad vicum Pontis London, Conſuetudo quae vocatur Scavagium, Conſuetudo quae vocatur Gauge,</hi> But
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:157030:59"/> yet more ſpecially it was applyed to that dutie, which we following the ſame rule, becauſe of the greatneſſe of the Revenue, doe likewiſe <hi>per Excellentiam,</hi> call Cuſtom; This may appeare by the Pipe Roll of 52. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. this title <hi>Conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo Mercandizorum,</hi> and by divers other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. times, the Rolls and Records of the beginning of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1, doe likewiſe prove the ſame very evidently, Inſomuch, that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which in this kinde belongs to the King by the Common Law, and by ancient preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was called <hi>Conſuetudo;</hi> but in later time, if any increaſe were of that dutie, though it came not by preſcription, but by grant in Parliament, or otherwiſe, yet it ſtill retained the name <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo,</hi> which by continuance of time, came to be the proper name to that kinde of dutie how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it began; And therefore in 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. you ſhall finde that after the old cuſtome of Woolls was increaſed to a demy-Marke by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, yet the word <hi>conſuetudo</hi> was neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtill retained, but with an addition, For it was then called <hi>nova conſuetudo.</hi> Nay, though the increaſe were by the Kings abſolute autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and upon the matter, a meere Impoſition, Yet the King in his Commiſſion did alwayes call it <hi>conſuetudo,</hi> as in 16. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. the Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Foure Shillings upon a Tun of Wine, is in the Kings Commiſſion to collect it, called <hi>conſuetudo.</hi> Nevertheleſſe, I aſſure my ſelf, the people called it by ſome worſe name, as <hi>Maletolt</hi> or the like.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:157030:60"/>
            <p> The ſeverall applications of this word <hi>Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudo</hi> to all duties whatſoever belonging to the Crowne by reaſon of Trade, is the reaſon as I conceive that the word is uſed in the plurall number in the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta, per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquas &amp; certas conſuetudines,</hi> that ſo they might bee ſecure againſt all unjuſt exactions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Merchandizes whatſoever; but as I have ſaid, the principall ſcope was to provide againſt Impoſitions, and by reaſon alſo that the word <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> was taken as well for Impoſitions as for rightfull Cuſtomes, therefore to make all ſure, they inſert the words <hi>antiquas &amp; rectas.</hi> This word <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> in this ſenſe continued till about the twentieth yeere of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. after which time I cannot call to minde that I have ſeene it upon any Record: In ſtead and place thereof came in the word <hi>Cuſtuma,</hi> which I find firſt in <hi>Charta Mercatoria an.</hi> 31. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. where the increaſe of Cuſtome by the grant of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-ſtrangers is called <hi>parva cuſtuma,</hi> &amp; that which before was called <hi>nova Conſuetudo</hi> doth now begin to loſe that name, and to bee called <hi>magna Cuſtuma,</hi> which termes of <hi>magna Cuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> intending thereby that increaſe made by Parliament, <hi>anno</hi> 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. upon the three ſtaple commodities, Wools, Wooll-fells, and Lether: And <hi>parva Cuſtuma,</hi> intending thereby the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe granted by the Merchants-ſtrangers, <hi>an.</hi> 31 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Cuſtums.</note> are the termes uſed at this day by the Cuſtomers, and by which they diſtinguiſh
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:157030:60"/> their entries. This word <hi>Cuſtuma</hi> I finde to have been alſo promiſcuouſly uſed by <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>E.</hi> 2. and <hi>E.</hi> 3. in their Commiſſions, and applyed as well to increaſe of Cuſtome by way of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or by acts of Parliament of thoſe times, as to ancient cuſtome upon the Staple commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but regularly none ought to be called <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuma</hi> but that which is due upon the Staple commodities, and ſo is it uſed at this day, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only cloath; for, if it bee laid by act of Parliament, it is called a <hi>Subſidie;</hi> if without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament <hi>Impoſt.</hi> You ſee in what ſenſe the words <hi>malum Tolnetum,</hi> and the word <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> have been uſed in former times, and are thereby able to judge how they ought to be underſtood in this preſent Statute which, as I have ſaid, ought to have the moſt benign inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation that the words may beare.</p>
            <p>But it hath beene likewiſe objected that in this Statute there is a ſpeciall clauſe of exception which leaveth the king at his liberty to lay what impoſitions he pleaſeth,<note place="margin">The third ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt <hi>Magna Charta, cap.</hi> 30. that by the Exception the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to lay Impoſitions is ſalved, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> this Statute not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, and that is the words in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Statute. All Merchants <hi>(if they were not openly prohibited before)</hi> ſhall have their paſſage, &amp;c. which implies, ſay they, that if they be prohibited (which reſts wholly in the kings power) then they are not to have benefit of this Stat. touching the freedome from impoſitions; and they ſay farther, that the very laying of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions doth imply a reſtraint <hi>ſub modo.</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:157030:61"/> Though I purpoſe to ſpeake more fully in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of this objection when I come to ſhew you the weakneſſe of the reaſons alledged for Impoſitions, yet I cannot forbeare in this place to ſpeake a word or two in anſwere thereof, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Statute now before us: <hi>Except they be prohibited they ſhall have free paſſage</hi> (ſaith the Statute) <hi>without paying Evill-toll;</hi> This doth imply, ſay they, that if they be prohibited they may be compelled to pay Impoſitions; but that cannot be neceſſarily concluded; it implies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſomewhat ſtrongly, that they may bee prohibited. The Statute of 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. cap. 12. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiteth the warden of the Fleete to deliver a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny priſoner out of execution, unleſſe it bee by writ or other commandment of the king. It may be as ſtrongly implied out of this Statute that the king may, by his commandment with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out writ,<note place="margin">4 &amp; 5 <hi>P. &amp; M. fo.</hi> 162. <hi>b. Dyer.</hi>
               </note> deliver a priſoner out of execution; but the contrary hath alwaies been held. The ſame objection is made, and the ſame anſwere may be given to another exception in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of this branch, <hi>Except in the time of war.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come to the ſecond Statute againſt Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions,<note place="margin">The ſecond Statute againſt Impoſitions, the Statute <hi>De Tallagio non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedendo,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and cleered.</note> which is the Statute <hi>de Tallagio non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedendo,</hi> touching the time of the making of which there is great variety of opinion; for it is not, for ought I could ever learne, found any where upon Record; Juſtice <hi>Raſtall</hi> accounts it to have beene made 51 of <hi>H.</hi> 3. and with him agrees an old manuſcript which I have ſeen: It
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:157030:61"/> may well bee, for in one of the Statutes you ſhall finde a pardon to <hi>Humfrey</hi> Earle of <hi>Boham</hi> Earle of Hertford and Eſſex, Conſtable of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and to <hi>Roger Bygott</hi> Earle of Norfolke and Suffolk marſhall of England, who both lived in that time. <hi>Tho.</hi> of Walſingham in his hiſtory of England, ſaith it was made in the 25 yeere of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. hee reciteth the Statute <hi>de verbo in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum</hi> as it is in our printed bookes, otherwiſe I ſhould have thought he had meant another Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute againſt Impoſitions made indeede 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1 and found upon the Records of that yeere, in our printed Statutes at large, it is placed laſt of all the Statutes of <hi>E.</hi> 1. Though there be ſome diſagreement about the time of the making of this Statute, yet they all agree the occaſion to be the laying of a great impoſition upon Wool, the words of <hi>Tho. Walſingham, Auxit Rex tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Lanae ad</hi> 40<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. <hi>cum prius ultra dimidiam mercam non daretur tota autem comunitas ſentit ſe gravatam de vectigali Lana enim Angliae fere extendit ad medietatem valoris terrae &amp; vectigal ad quintam partem terrae.</hi> The Cuſtome of Wools as you perceive was in thoſe dayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed to bee the fift part of the value of the whol land; it followeth, in him, that upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint the Subject at laſt obteined the Statute I now ſpeake of, the words of which are, <hi>No Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage or Ayde ſhall bee rayſed or ſet by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s or our Heires in Our Realm, without the aſſent and good will of Arch-biſhops, Earles, Barons, Knights, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:157030:62"/> and other Freemen of the Land,</hi> after theſe generall words, by way of proviſion againſt all manner of burthens whatſoever to bee laid in time to come, without aſſent of Parliament, followeth in the next branch, ſave one eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all proviſion for the taking away of the impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then in demand upon Wools, which latter clauſe, as it doth cleerely ſhew the cauſe of their preſent griefe to bee the ſame which our Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles ſay it was, ſo doth it likewiſe make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent what it was which they ſought to be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of for the times to come; neither are the words themſelves ſo obſcure, by reaſon of the generalty of them, but that they alſo without knowing the occaſion of the making of the law doe directly point at Impoſitions; for, though indeede the word <hi>Tallage</hi> be (as I conceive) to bee underſtood only of charges within the Land,<note place="margin">Tallage.</note> yet the word <hi>Ayde</hi> extendeth to all char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of what nature ſoever;<note place="margin">Aydes.</note> nay, that even Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions themſelves have beene called <hi>Aydes</hi> or <hi>Subſidies</hi> (which is all one) is evident by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Records of the Exchequor here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, eſpecially by thoſe of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. time; in which, whereſoever you finde any mention made by the King, in his Commiſſions, of an impoſition raiſed by him, hee ever calls it <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> or <hi>Auxilium;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Subſidies.</note> So likewiſe in the printed Statute of 36 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. cap. 11. you ſhall finde that the Impoſition by grant of Merchants there mentioned is called a <hi>Subſidie or Ayde:</hi> This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:157030:62"/> of the word <hi>Ayde,</hi> concurring with the occaſion of the making of the Statute, doth in my opinion ſtrongly enforce this Statute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Impoſitions; and 'tis to bee obſerved that in this Stat. there is <hi>no ſaving or exception of the kings antient Right,</hi> which (as our Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſay) was a point principally inſiſted upon at the making of this Law, earneſtly preſſed by the Subject to bee without that clauſe, and for a long while ſtood upon by the king, but at laſt yeelded unto in ſuch ſort as you have heard.</p>
            <p>The next Statute againſt Impoſitions is 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. cap. 7.<note place="margin">The third Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute againſt Impoſitions, 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. cleered from objections.</note> the words are, <hi>Foraſmuch as the more part of the Cominalty hath found themſelves ſore agrieved with the Male-tolt of Wools,</hi> viz. <hi>a toll of</hi> 40<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 
               <hi>for every ſack of Wool, and have made pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to bee releaſed of the ſame, Wee at their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts have cleerely releaſed it, and have granted for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and our Heires, that Wee ſhall take no ſuch, things without their common aſſent and good will, ſaving to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and our Heires the cuſtome of Wools, Skins and Leather granted before by the Cominalty aforeſaid.</hi> I might, in enforcing this Statute, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon a rule of Law for the expoſition of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this nature, <hi>Omnis Impoſitio eſt odioſa, ideo ſtricta contra Impoſitiones, &amp; large ad favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem gravatorum interpretanda eſt lex contra Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitiones data,</hi> but there ſhall not need any ſuch favorable conſtruction; for the words are in themſelves very cleere. The Law conſiſteth of three parts; the firſt is the kings grant of a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:157030:63"/> petition made by the Commons, for the relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of an Impoſition of 40<hi rend="sup">s</hi> upon a ſack of Wool, then in demand; when the preſent grief was ended, the next care was to prevent the like miſchiefe in all times to come; It therfore folowes, <hi>And Wee have granted for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and Our Heires that Wee ſhall take no ſuch thing without their common aſſent,</hi> which is the ſecond part of the law; The ſaving in the end is the third part.</p>
            <p>Againſt this generall proviſion, two obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions have beene made.<note place="margin">The firſt obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that this Statute is only againſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Impoſitions then laid, and not againſt the right of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, anſwered.</note> Firſt, that the words <hi>No ſuch things</hi> are to be underſtood only of the burthenſomneſſe and exceſſe of Impoſitions, and not otherwiſe. <hi>No ſuch things</hi> (that is, ſay they) No <hi>ſuch grievous</hi> Impoſitions as this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Impoſition is. It had beene a poore ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for times to come, to have left it to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, whether or no, Impoſitions which might happen to be laid in after ages be as grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous as the Impoſition complained of in this time? by comparing one with the other; 'tis ſo uncertain a computation, as no man (when hee thinks throughly of it) can imagine that men, worthy to ſit at the making of Laws, ſhould ſuffer ſuch a thing to paſſe them. Who can certainly ſay whether our Impoſitions bee more or leſſe grievous then the rate of 40<hi rend="sup">s</hi> upon a ſack of Wool: Beſide, how eaſily had this Lawe beene to have beene deluded by abating only 12<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, or but 1<hi rend="sup">d</hi> in the next Impoſition; for, if it be but a penny leſſe, it is <hi>No ſuch</hi> Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:157030:63"/> for the burden; Therefore it muſt needes bee expounded of the quality and very nature of the thing complained of,<note place="margin">26 Ed. 1. <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brevia ret<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn. de Term. Mich. in Scac. in offic. Rem. Theſaurar. ibidem.</hi>
               </note> and not of the quantity. <hi>No ſuch thing</hi> (that is) <hi>No ſuch thing as this is</hi> (that is to ſay) <hi>an Impoſition:</hi> But that which will cleere this objection is a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made the very next yeer after the making of this Act, in which the king reciting this Act, in ſtead of theſe words, Wee will take <hi>No ſuch thing,</hi> uſeth theſe words <hi>Nullam aliam Cuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ſine communi conſenſu Capiemus,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>No ſuch,</hi> but <hi>no other:</hi> By which you may ſee that the words were then interpreted in that ſence in which I doe now interpret them.</p>
            <p>But admitting, ſay they,<note place="margin">The ſecond objection, that is only againſt Impoſitions upon Wool, anſwered.</note> that it bee ſo to bee expounded that the king will lay <hi>No other Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> without aſſent in Parliament, that is to be uuderſtood, ſay they, <hi>No other Impoſition upon, Wools,</hi> and not otherwiſe; which is their ſecond objection. It were a very ſtrict conſtruction for a Statute of ſo beneficiall an intent as this is ſo to reſtraine it; if there were no other words in the Statute that did inlarge the expoſition, But by the words following it is moſt evident that the ſcope of this Law is more liberall then ſo, and that the kings intent was for ever to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his Subjects againſt all charges of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I meane Impoſitions, not upon Wools only but upon any other Merchandize whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, which I collect from laying all the parts of the Law together.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:157030:64"/>
            <p> The Petition for preſent eaſe is to be relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed onely of the <hi>Maletolt</hi> of foure ſhillings upon a ſack of Wooll, which is yeelded to: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for the time to come, is, <hi>We will take no ſuch thing:</hi> The ſaving which followeth that, is, <hi>Saving the Cuſtome of Woolls, Woolfells, and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> I obſerve, the ſaving extends not to <hi>woolls</hi> alone, as the Petition doth, but alſo to Wooll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fells and Leather, by expreſſe name; by which it is evident, that the ſecuritie for the time to come is of a larger extent than to ſtretch onely to Woolls, as hath been objected: For elſe, to what end ſhould Wooll-fells and Leather be excepted in the ſaving, if they had not been contained in the generall words, <hi>no ſuch thing.</hi> An exception cannot be but of a thing contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in former words: If therefore the grant would have extended to Wooll-fells, if they had not been ſpecially excepted; then doe I conclude by the ſame reaſon, that it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to all other Merchandizes not excepted; for the words are generall. And ſo I leave this Law cleered of all objections, and very full a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>The next Statute made againſt them, is, 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">The fourth Statute urged againſt Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, 14 <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. cleered from objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 21. By the firſt part of which Law you may perceive, that whereas the Commons had prayed the King not to take of Woolls, Wooll-fells, Leather, Tyn, or Lead any more than the ancient Cuſtome, the King prayed them to grant him forty ſhillings upon a ſack of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:157030:64"/> Wooll for a yeer and a halfe, which they gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: whereupon the King, by way of Retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in anſwere of their Petition, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Wooll cauſeth it to be enacted for their Security in time to come, <hi>That neither he nor his heires would demand, aſſeſſe, nor take more cuſtome of a ſack of Wooll than ſixe ſhillings eight pence: And ſo likewiſe upon Woolls and Leather, no more than the ancient cuſtome, without aſſent of Parliament.</hi> All this while there is no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer given touching the Tyn and Lead menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Petition; upon which, as it appears, the King had alſo laid Impoſitions: But there doe follow certain generall words by which, not onely Tyn and Lead, but all other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities whatſoever are freed from Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The words are, <hi>The King promiſed in the preſence of his Earles, Barons, and others of his Parliament, no more to charge, ſet, or aſſeſſe upon the Cuſtome, but in manner aforeſaid.</hi> Except theſe words doe extend to Lead and Tyn, to free them from Impoſitions for times to come, as well as woolls, wooll-fells, and Leather are freed by the former ſpeciall words, their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching Tyn and Lead is no way anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: And if they doe extend to Tyn and Lead, by reaſon of the generalty of the words, they doe by the ſame reaſon extend to all commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: For what more liberall words can there be than theſe; <hi>That the King will not charge, ſet, or aſſeſſe upon the cuſtome:</hi> theſe words, <hi>the cuſtome,</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:157030:65"/> being words indefinite, are (you know) equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to an Univerſall, according to the rule, <hi>Indefinitum aequipollet univerſali:</hi> And although the King doe but promiſe, yet I doubt not but in this caſe his promiſe is a Law: And it is worth the obſerving, that the Lords doe in very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary and unuſuall manner ſolemnly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, as much as in them lyeth, that they ſhall procure the King to hold the ſame, and <hi>that they ſhall in no wiſe aſſent to the contrary, if it be not by the aſſent of the Prelates, Earles, Barons and Commons, and that in full Parliament;</hi> and for the greater ſurety, and to give cauſe to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew all counſell to the contrary of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>the Prelates have promiſed to give ſentence upon them that counſell againſt the ſame in any point;</hi> which are the very words of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in print.</p>
            <p>The Statute of 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. was yeilded unto by the King,<note place="margin">13. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 5. Ro. Par.</hi>
               </note> upon a Petition exhibited the Parliament before, both by the Lords and the Commons, praying that a Law might be made againſt Impoſitions, as may appeare by the Records of the 13 yeere of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. at which time they likewiſe prayed, that the King would be pleaſed to grant them a Charter to the ſame effect, to be inrolled in Parliament: The Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute you have heard; the Charter followeth in our printed bookes immediately after the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, where the King (in the preamble thereof) reciting the great gift that he had given him at
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:157030:65"/> the ſame Parliament, that is to ſay, the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Fleece,</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Sheep, &amp;</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Lamb</hi> throughout the Kingdom, which indeed, was a very extraordinary great guift; and therefore his grant, in regard there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is to be intended ſo much more beneficially) doth in lieu thereof, for him and his heires, grant to his Subjects in theſe words; <hi>From henceforth they ſhall not be charged, nor grieved, to make any ayde, or to ſuſteine charge, if it be not by the Common aſſent of the Prelates, Earles, Barons and other great men, and the Commons of our ſaid realme of England, and that in Parliament.</hi> It hath been objected, that theſe words, <hi>Aide</hi> and <hi>Charge,</hi> are to be underſtood of Charges within the Land, ſuch as are Taxes and Tallages,<note place="margin">An Objection that the ſtat. of 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>An.</hi> 21 extendeth only to Impoſitions within the land and not to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon Merchandizes, is anſwered.</note> and not of Impoſitions upon Merchandizes; And this is the only Objection made, or indeed can be made againſt this Statute; For the cleering of which, I can ſay no more then already I have proved by matter of Record for the opening of the ſenſe of this Statute, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Charter, and the laſt Statute were made upon a Petition exhibited in Parliament, for a law and Charter to be made againſt Impoſitions upon Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes. And therefore that conjecture of theirs, that it ſhould extend only to Taxes, and not to Impoſitions, cannot but fall to the ground, eſpecially ſince there is not in the Petition, any mention at all of Taxes or Tallages, or of any other charge or aide but impoſitions onely, then which there cannot allmoſt be a cleerer proof,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:157030:66"/> then that this Law being made upon this Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is to be expounded againſt Impoſitions; which, if this Petition had not been extant, would with no leſſe cleerneſſe have been proved by conſidering the miſchiefe at the time of the making of this law, which was not Tallage or Taxes, but thoſe heavie Impoſitions of Foure pound, and five pound upon a ſack of Wooll, by way of diſpenſation with the Statute of 11. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. of which I have formerly made menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So as this Statute, being made in the firſt intention againſt diſpenſations for money, with a penall law, though the occaſion were particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, yet (the words being generall) <hi>I hold that with reaſon it may be extended againſt all diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with penall lawes for money:</hi> in particular, I hold, that the raiſing of money by <hi>diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> with the Statutes againſt Ale-houſes, is (if not by the Common Law) yet by the force of this law, unlawfull, For certainly, <hi>quod prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt una viae, non debet alia permitti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the words <hi>Ayde</hi> and <hi>Charge,</hi> I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proved that it was a terme by which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions were commonly called in thoſe times; That they were alſo called <hi>charges</hi> is evident by very many Records of thoſe times,<note place="margin">The word Charge.</note> where complaint is made againſt them, as 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. <hi>Les commons prion qe la charge de</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ſur ſack de lane ſoit Ouſte,</hi> 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 16. <q>The Commons pray that no <hi>charge</hi> be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them without aſſent of Parliament.</q> The
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:157030:66"/> kings anſwere is, if any <hi>Impoſition</hi> be levyed unduely it ſhall bee taken away; of this kinde there are very many Preſidents, ſo as if the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Petition had not aſſured us of the ſcope of this Lawe as it doth, the very words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, rightly underſtood, would have made it cleere.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Charter there is another clauſe as beneficiall as this, to this effect, <hi>All Merchants Denizens &amp; Forreins (except thoſe which be of our enmitie) may without let ſafely come into the Relm of England with their goods and Merchandizes, and ſafely tarry, and ſafely returne, paying the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, ſubſidies and other profits</hi> reaſonably thereof due. The objection to this clauſe is very obvious, for what (ſay they) can theſe words, Other profits <hi>reaſonably due</hi> ſignifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>Impoſitions;</hi> for, by the words going before, Cuſtome and Subſidies are expreſly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and there is (ſay they) no other third profit upon Merchandize but Impoſitions, and indeed this Statute they themſelves have vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in maintenance of Impoſitions. To this objection it might ſerve for a full anſwer, that there are other duties then Cuſtomes and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies due upon the landing of wares; for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Wharfage, Cranage, Scavage</hi> and ſuch like, the which with more probability I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture to be intended by theſe words, <hi>Other duties,</hi> then they can conjecture it to bee meant of <hi>Impoſitions, Sed in planis non opus eſt conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturis.</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:157030:67"/> The beſt expoſitors of this Act are thoſe that lived in the ſame times, and they doe cleerely expound this clauſe to be made againſt Impoſitions, as may appeare by the Record of 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>No.</hi> 29. for you ſhall there finde a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion exhibited in Parliament by the Commons to bee relieved touching an Impoſition upon Wools, alledging for a reaſon of their Petition, that every <hi>man ought freely to paſſe paying the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient cuſtome as it was ordained by the kings Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> This Petition againſt Impoſitions was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by the whole Parliament, within ſix yeeres after the making of the Charter, as may appeare by comparing the times, and if they had not then thought that <hi>Impoſitions</hi> had been meant to have beene provided againſt by this Charter, they would not certainly have made ſuch a ſpeciall reference thereunto. In diſcovering the weakeneſſe of the reaſons alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in maintenance of Impoſitions,<note place="margin">Anſwers to the Reaſons urged in maintenance of Impoſitions</note> I ſhall not greatly neede to ſay any thing more then hath been ſaid, becauſe the ſtate of the queſtion hath beene already ſo throughly opened unto you, that whatſoever can with any colour of reaſon be ſaid for Impoſitions, may receive an anſwer out of that which hath beene ſpoken againſt them: Nevertheleſſe, I will in a few words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to your memories their reaſons, and in as few apply the anſwers to them, with ſome addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mine owne, that by laying both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your view at one time, the weakeneſſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:157030:67"/> of the one, and ſtrength of the other may the better appeare unto you.</p>
            <p>It hath beene ſaid that the old Cuſtome of a Demi-marke upon a ſack of VVool muſt have his beginning either by the kings abſolute po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,<note place="margin">The firſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot appear that the ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes were ſet by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, therefore they were impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the King, anſwered</note> or by a legall aſſent of the people, which can bee no where but in Parliament, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but appeare of Record; but becauſe no ſuch aſſent can be ſhowne, therefore they conclude that it began by the kings abſolute power, and inferre that the ſame power remaines ſtill. The ſubſtance of this argument is found in my Lord <hi>Dyer</hi> in the place cyted by me; It was much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced in the Exchequer: but as touching the particular of the old Cuſtome of a Demi-marke upon a ſack, and the other old cuſtom upon Fels and Leather, it is now no longer urged becauſe it appeares expreſly by divers Records of 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. in the Tower, That it was granted <hi>per les grandes et al prier des Comons et de les Merchants de tout Englaterre,</hi> and by a Record of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. Stat. printed, <hi>per Communitatem Regni noſtri Angliae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. Pat. 3. <hi>E.</hi> 3. M. 1. Stat. 25. E. 1. c. 7. Ro. fin. intus 3 E. 1. M. 24.</note> which concurres alſo with the Statute of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. in print. Saving to Us and our Heires the Cuſtomes of wools, ſkins and leather <hi>granted heretofore</hi> by the Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid. The <hi>Pattent roll</hi> of 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. which hath theſe words <hi>cum Prelati Magnates ac tota Comunitas Mercatorum Regni noſtri nuper nobis conceſſerunt quandam novam conſuetudinem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. M. 1. Ro. Par.</note> viz. <hi>de quolibet ſacco Lanae</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:157030:68"/> thing obſcure are by the concurrence of all thoſe other Records ſo cleerely expounded, as there cannot be, neither now is there, any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion made but that the Cuſtome of a Demy-marke, and the other old Cuſtomes, which by my Lord <hi>Dyer,</hi> and by all thoſe who argued for, or againſt Impoſitions in the Exchequer, was held to bee due by the Common-Lawe, was by grant in Parliament; nevertheleſſe the ſtrength of the argument they ſtill retaine, though the Demy-mark and thoſe old Cuſtomes upon the ſtaple commodities were by Act of Parliament, yet (ſay they) before that increaſe by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the king had Cuſtome, and no doubt a ſome certaine, otherwiſe could not this increaſe be called <hi>nova conſuetudo;</hi> beſides (ſay they) the Cuſtome reduced to a certainty by 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. is only upon three commodities, wool, ſkins, and leather: there are many other commodities which did likewiſe pay Cuſtome; How began that Cuſtome (ſay they) if not by the kings ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power? and when was that power taken away? I anſwere, admit it were by the kings abſolute power, yet that the king hath cleerely diſcharged himſelf of that power by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, I hope I have cleerely proved: But this queſtion, How began the firſt Cuſtoms? is beſt anſwered by another queſtion, How began the Fine for purchaſe of Originall VVrits? the Fine <hi>pro licentia concordandi?</hi> the certainty of priſage? nay, who reduced it firſt to certaintie
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:157030:68"/> that the tryall of iſſues ſhould be by twelve Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, no more nor no leſſe? that the full age of a man ſhould bee accounted twenty one yeers? of a woman fourteene, twelve yeeres her age of conſent, and nine yeeres capable to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed? a yeere and a day given to ſue an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, the like limitation of a yeere and day in very many other Caſes? In effect, who redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all the known grounds of the Common law to that certainty that now they are? Becauſe wee cannot tell how or when they began, ſhall wee therfore conclude that they began by the kings abſolute power, and inferre, that by the ſame reaſon, they may bee changed at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? If the king may increaſe his Fines upon the purchaſe of Originall writts (which by the ſame reaſon hee may doe, that hee may doe his Cuſtome, nay, hee hath more colour for this then for that, becauſe there is no Statute againſt this) hee might eaſily raiſe that revenue to the value of his Cuſtomes: But no man can, nor will I hope offer to mainteine it to bee lawfull. You ſee the weakeneſſe and the dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of this argument, by comparing it to other caſes of like nature. To ſay the truth, all theſe things began no man can ſay certainly when or how, but by a tacit conſent of king and people, and the long approbation of time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the memory of any man, and yet no man can directly affirm but that moſt of them might begin by Act of Parliament, though now there
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:157030:69"/> bee no Records extant of ſuch antient Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The firſt Parliament was not kept 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3 though it be the firſt in our bookes. If we will give credit to other Records, and to our beſt Chroniclers,<note place="margin">The antiquity of Parliaments</note> we ſhall heare and reade of divers Parliaments in the Reigne of King <hi>John,</hi> and of his Predeceſſor <hi>Rich.</hi> 1. and in the Reign of <hi>H.</hi> 2. of two famous Parliaments, one at Claringdon in Wiltſhire, the other at Gedington in North-Hamptonſhire: And although our Chronicles ſay, that the firſt Parliament kept in this Realm was held 19 <hi>Aprilis,</hi> 16 <hi>H.</hi> 1. yet I am of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror held Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for what can be elſe underſtood by theſe words, <hi>Per commune conſilium totius Regni noſtri ſtabilitum fuit,</hi> which I finde in Mr. <hi>Lamberts</hi> collection of the ancient Lawes of England, in the beginning of the Lawes of <hi>W.</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: Many of the Statutes of <hi>E.</hi> 1. have no other words: Nay, long before him, in the yeere of our Lord 712. in the time of <hi>Inas</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> I aſſure my ſelfe there were Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments held, and that of the three Eſtates, as at this day; as may appeare by theſe words in the beginning of the Lawes of King <hi>Inas,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Lambert: Suaſu &amp; Inſtituto Epiſcoporum noſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omnium, Senatorum noſtrorum, &amp; natu ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorum populi noſtri in frequentia magna:</hi> And more plainly in the concluſion of ſome other of his Lawes; <hi>Hoc factum fuit per commune con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium &amp; aſſenſum Procerum, Comitum, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:157030:69"/> Sapientium, Seniorum, &amp; Populorum toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Regni, &amp; per praeceptum Regis Inae,</hi> which are the ſame in Latine which ours is in Engliſh, <hi>By the King, the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons.</hi> VVhy might not the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome upon Woolls be firſt granted at one of theſe Parliaments, as well as to have it firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by the Kings abſolute power? There is no more probability of the one than the other: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe moſt of the ancient Records were burnt in <hi>H.</hi> 2. time, when the Exchequer was burnt, ſhall we conclude therefore that there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er any ſuch? You ſee the weaknes of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in all the points thereof. I leave it, and paſſe to another.</p>
            <p>The King may (ſay they) reſtrain the paſſage of Merchants at his pleaſure,<note place="margin">The ſecond Argument, that the King may totally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chandizes, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he may do it <hi>ſub modo</hi> by laying of an Impoſition, anſwered.</note> which they prove by divers Records; 2 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>m.</hi> 18. <hi>Ro. Par.</hi> 2 <hi>E</hi> 1. <hi>m.</hi> 17. <hi>Ro. fin.</hi> 31 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 44. <hi>Ro. Pat.</hi> 17 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Ro. Clo. in dorſo:</hi> Upon which they inferre, that if he may reſtraine a Merchant that he ſhall not paſſe at all, he may much more ſo reſtraine him that he ſhall not paſſe except he pay a certaine ſum of money: For this (ſay they) is leſſe than totally to reſtraine him; And <hi>(Cui licet quod ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, licet etiam quod minus.)</hi> Of this Argument my L. <hi>Dyer</hi> gave light in his caſe of Impoſitions, 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and this hath been diverſly inforced by all that have argued for Impoſitions. In anſwer of which I will conſider how farre the king may reſtrain the paſſage of Merchants; and then will
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:157030:70"/> examine the conſequence of the Argument.</p>
            <p>For my part, I think the king cannot reſtrain the paſſage of Merchants, but for ſome ſpeciall cauſe; wherein to define certainly and reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſay for what cauſes he may, and for what not, I will not undertake: Onely let me inform you, that there is not one of theſe preſidents vouched by them to prove the kings power to reſtraine, but they are upon ſpeciall reaſons; as by reaſon of Enmity with ſuch a Nation from whence they are reſtrained, or becauſe ſuch a Commodity may not be ſpared within the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Beſides, they are not reſtraints from all places, and of all manner of Merchandizes, but from certain places onely, and for certain ſorts of Merchandizes: And for my part I thinke that reſtraints in all theſe caſes, and of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are by the Common-Law left to the kings abſolute power; For if it were otherwiſe, it ſhould be in the power of a Merchant, for a little private lucre, to enrich the kings Enemies, or to furniſh them with munition to be imployed againſt the State, or utterly to ruine the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, by carrying out a Commodity which may not be ſpared, or by bringing in of ſome that may be hurtfull. Nay (which is more) ſuch may be the occaſion, that the king may, I doubt not, ſtop the paſſages of all Merchants from all places for a ſhort time, as upon the death of the late Queene it was put in practiſe, to prevent Intelligence: there may likewiſe be
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:157030:70"/> ſuch neceſſary uſe of their ſhips, as the want of them, upon ſome ſodaine attempts, may be a cauſe of the overthrow of the whole State. In ſuch caſes as theſe, if the Common law did not give the King leave to reſtraine their paſſage by his abſolute power, it were very improvident in the higheſt points, which cannot be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of ſo wiſe a law; And yet the Kings of this Realme have alwayes been ſparing in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of their abſolute power in this point, For there are little leſſe then 30. Acts of Parliament, touching the opening and ſhutting up of the paſſage of Merchants, moſt of which, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, were made rather for the increaſe of puniſhment, then for want of power in the King, For the breach of a reſtraint by abſolute commandment, is puniſhable, as all other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, onely by Fine and Impriſonment, and not by forfeiture of the Merchandizes, as in the preſident of the Wines, <hi>An.</hi> 5. of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> vouched by me, and is in ſome of thoſe old pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents. If it be otherwiſe, I muſt confeſſe I know not the reaſon of the difference of this from other contempts. You ſee that I have yeelded to their propoſition, <hi>That the King may by his abſolute power reſtraine the paſſage ef Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi> and have therein granted, more then their preſidents prove; But is the conſequence good, that becauſe the King may reſtrain, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he may impoſe upon ſuch as paſſe? Firſt I denie that in our caſe there is any reſtraint at
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:157030:71"/> all, as there was in the caſe of the French Wines, by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> by her Proclamation going before the impoſition. For proofe of which, I referre you to the Kings Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents prefixed before the laſt Book of Rates, by which inſtrument, the impoſitions now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, were altogether raiſed, you ſhall finde it no other then a Declaration of the Kings pleaſure ſo to have it, and a courſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for levying of it; But admitting that the very laying of an impoſition, did implie a reſtraint, yet I denie the conſequence, Becauſe the King may reſtraine totally, that therefore he may reſtraine for a time, or from certaine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or certaine commodities, or certaine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants. This indeed is a good Argument, <hi>a majori ad minus.</hi> But becauſe he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine totally, therefore that he may give paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for money, is no good conſequence; For in our caſe, there is no reſtraint at all, but it is rather a paſſage for money. If there be juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a reſtraint, the law giveth the King power to reſtraine; but when Merchants may without hurt of the State, have paſſage, as in our caſe, to enforce them to pay for that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, is in my opinion, as unlawfull as to enforce any man whatſoever, to pay for doing that which he may lawfully doe; Merchants have (as I may ſo ſay) as good inheritance in their trade, as any man in his lands, and when it may ſtand with the good of the ſtate, that they may
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:157030:71"/> paſſe, they ought to paſſe as freely without charge impoſed on them, as any man ought to hold his inheritance, or any Artificer, or other Tradeſman ought to exerciſe their lawfull trades, and means of living, free from burdens to be laid on by the Kings abſolute power; if all others ſhould be free, and onely Merchants, (who adventure their perſons and eſtates in ſo many dangers, to bring us from farre places, ſuch things, as without which we cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and to returne us profit for our ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) ſhould be ſubject to involuntarie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, their eſtate were of all other mens moſt unhappy and ſlaviſh, which of all other trades, is indeed the nobleſt, and moſt worthy to be cheriſhed.</p>
            <p>And here by the way I note, that in all other Nations of the world, where the Merchant is ſubject to impoſitions at the Kings pleaſure, the Landlord, the Farmer, the Artificer, the very Plowman, and all others are in like ſort ſubject to Taxes and burdens, when the King pleaſeth, The Merchant is not the man alone that is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Taxes, and all other men free: if in the frame of our Common wealth, it were thought fit to free all other Trades and Profeſſions from taxes, much more ought it to be thought reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that our Merchants ſhould be free, and by all means poſſible, incouraged in their Trade: For our caſe is not, as it is with other nations of the Continent; we are Iſlanders, and divided
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:157030:72"/> by the Sea, from all the world, and in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, have ſuch uſe of Merchants, as we cannot live without them; if therefore any ſhould be free amongſt us, it ſhould be the Merchant, and not the quite contrary, onely the Merchant charged, and all others free: <hi>Plato</hi> in his 8. book <hi>de Rep.</hi> is of opinion, that the Merchant for his incouragement to trade, ſhould be free from all Cuſtome whatſoever, we ſeek only to be free of involuntary impoſitions. But to return to the Argument of reſtraint, from whence I am a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle digreſſed; if it be a good Argument, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King may reſtraine in <hi>Toto,</hi> he may reſtrain in <hi>Tanto;</hi> It will not be denied unto me (for it followeth neceſſarily) that in caſes where he cannot reſtraine in <hi>Toto,</hi> he cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine in <hi>Tanto:</hi> But there is no man that will ſay that he may reſtraine the entrance and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of all Merchants, to and from all the parts of the world whatſoever, without any limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time, but the reſtraint to endure for ever, and for all kinds of Merchandizes whatſoever, of moſt neceſſary and common uſe, to be brought into, or carried out of the Realme; There is no man I ſuppoſe will ſay, That the Law hath given the King power to make ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable a reſtraint as this; for it were to give him a power to deſtroy merchandize, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, to ruine the Common wealth, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, it were againſt the law of nations, and of reaſon it ſelf; It cannot be imagined, that any
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:157030:72"/> wiſe law in the world ſhould allow it. But if our Impoſitions (as it is ſaid) doe implie a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and that a reſtraint be always the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of all Impoſitions, Then ſuch an unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable reſtraint, as I have ſpoken of, muſt needs be preſuppoſed to have been the ground or fore-runner of our preſent impoſition, For in our impoſitions, are not all the merchandizes of neceſſary and common uſe charged? Are not all the Merchants Denizens and Strangers, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting from any part, or exporting to any part of the world, ſubject to the charge? is there any limitation of time, but to endure for ever? if I ſay ſuch a reſtraint had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, which I ſuppoſe no man will denie, then whatſoever implieth ſuch a Reſtraint (which our impoſitions doe) is likewiſe unlawfull; But the ill conſequence of this their argument drawne from the Kings power of reſtraint, will beſt appeare by comparing it to other caſes.</p>
            <p>I little doubt but the King upon ſome occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, may lawfully reſtraine the paſſage of all men through the gates of <hi>London;</hi> as for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when the Citie ſhall be beſieged, or in the time of an extreme plague; Nay is it not by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie derived onely from him, that the gates are ſhut every night? Doth it follow therefore, that becauſe he may doe it upon ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary occaſion, or at ſome time that he may ſhut up the paſſage for ever? or that preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:157030:73"/> ſuch a reſtraint by his abſolute power, he may lay an impoſition upon every burthen of any thing brought in, or carried out, as the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> and many other States in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> doe, or upon every man by the Poll, that ſhall paſſe through the gates?</p>
            <p>You ſee the weakneſſe and danger of the conſequence of this Argument, and how it tends to juſtifie Impoſitions within the land. And ſo I leave it, and proceed to the next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Ports and Haven Townes of England, are (ſay they) the Kings,<note place="margin">The third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that the Ports are the Kings, and that he may open them, and ſhut them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, anſwered.</note> and in regard thereof, he may open and ſhut them upon what conditions he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth;</hi> I anſwere,</p>
            <p>I. That the Poſition, that all the Ports are the Kings, is not generally true; For Subjects may alſo be owners of Ports, as may appeare by the Patent Roll of 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>M.</hi> 1. Parl. where you ſhall finde, that King <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. granted to the <hi>Lords of Port Townes,</hi> the forfeitures granted to him by Parliament, for not duly paying the new Cuſtome of the demy-Marke within every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Port, of theirs, where the Merchandizes ſhould happen to be imported or exported. But admitting the truth of the poſition, yet is the conſequence as weake and dangerous, as of any of the reſt of their arguments; For are not all the gates of Cities and Townes, and all the Streets and Highwayes in England the Kings, and as much ſubject to be open or ſhut at his pleaſure, as the Ports are? Nay, whenſoever
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:157030:73"/> we ſpeake of the Highway in any law buſineſſe, we call it <hi>via Regia,</hi> the Kings Highway, and the King in his Commiſſions, ſpeaking of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> or any other Citie, calls it <hi>Civitas noſtra, London,</hi> or <hi>Civitas noſtra Exon;</hi> Doth it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low therefore, that the King may lay Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon every man, or upon all Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that ſhall paſſe through any of theſe places? Nay the gates of the Kings owne houſe (for the purpoſe, his Pallace of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) are his in a farre neerer degree then any of theſe, may he therefore by his Proclamation impoſe upon every man that ſhall paſſe in or out at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Hall doore a ſumme of money? Doubtleſſe he may not; becauſe the King is a perſon pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and his Subjects ought to have acceſſe to him, as to the fountaine of Juſtice, and to the Courts of Juſtice, ſitting by his authoritie; I make little doubt, but his Majeſtie may upon juſt occaſion, cauſe any of theſe paſſages to be ſhut, as he may alſo the paſſage at the Havens; But when the Paſſage may without danger to the State, be open, and that the Subjects may paſſe, his Majeſtie may not then exact money for their paſſage; For the law hath given the King power over theſe things, for the good of the Common-wealth, and not thereby to charge and burden the Subject; If the King may not exact money for paſſage in and out of his Court gates, becauſe of the publikeneſſe of his Perſon; Nor for paſſage through the gates
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:157030:74"/> of Cities, much leſſe may he for paſſage out at the Ports, which are the great gates of the Kingdom, and which the ſubject ought as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enjoy, as the ayre or the water.</p>
            <p>Another of their arguments is this,<note place="margin">The fourth argument that the King is bound at his owne charge, to protect Merchants, &amp; therefore it is neceſſary it ſhould be in his power to lay moderate Impoſitions upon Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes for raiſing of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to defray his charge; Anſwered.</note> 
               <hi>The king is bound to protect Merchants from ſpoile by the enemie, he ought to fortifie the Havens, that their ſhips may there abide in ſafety; he ought, if occaſion be, to ſend Ambaſſadors to forrein Princes, to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate for them,</hi> and many the like charges is the King by the Law to undergoe for the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Merchants. It is reaſon therefore that his expence be defraied out of the profit made by Merchants, and conſequently, that he may impoſe upon Merchandize a moderate charge, thereby to repay himſelf.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of this Argument is thus farre true, The law expects that the King ſhould protect Merchants, therefore it alloweth him out of Merchandize a revenue for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his charge, which is the old Cuſtome due (as at firſt I ſaid) by the Common law, But it is no good conſequence,<note place="margin">The Fifth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that all forraine Princes have power to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and if our King had not the like, it might be very inconvenient to this State. Anſwered.</note> that therefore he may take what he liſt, no more then he may at his pleaſure increaſe that old revenue, which the law giveth him for protecting of Subjects in their ſuits, or for protecting Wards, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Another Argument of theirs is this, <hi>All other Princes of the world may impoſe upon merchandize at their pleaſure, and ſo may make our Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes leſſe vendible with them, by laying an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:157030:74"/> upon them, to be paid by us, when they are brought into their Territories, whereby their owne Commodities of the ſame nature, may be ſold more to the gaine of their Merchants, and our Merchant impoveriſhed, or driven from his Trade; They may alſo lay Impoſitions upon our Merchants, fetching Commodities from thence, and leave their owne Merchants free from any Impoſition in the ſame caſe, by which their merchants ſhall reape all the profit by that commoditie, in affording it better cheape to us here, then we can fetch it, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our merchants ſhall be undone,</hi> Many the like caſes have been put to prove, That if the King of England may not impoſe, as other Princes may, they ſhall be able at their pleaſure to deſtroy our trading; This I conceive was the ſame as now it is, during all that time from <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. till Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and doubtleſſe it could not but ſometimes (during that long ſpace) ſo fall out, that forreine Princes did put their power in practiſe to our prejudice, and yet we heare not of any Impoſition laid by any of our Kings, by their abſolute power, which may give any man aſſurance, that they tooke ſome other courſe to meet with the inconvenience, and in deed, the meanes are divers, which theſe our Kings uſed to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Firſt they were carefull in all their Leagues and Treaties with forrain Princes, ſpecially to provide for it, as may appeare by the Records of the ancient Leagues: Neither is there any
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:157030:75"/> League of late time, that hath not had an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle for proviſion in this point; which Leagues for the moſt part, are upon oath on both parts. And yet for further ſecuritie, our Kings have always had Ambaſſadors reſident in the Courts of ſuch forrain Princes, to put them in minde of their Leagues, if upon any occaſion our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants have in that caſe happened to be never ſo little wronged by them, &amp; if upon complaint of the Ambaſſador, our merchants have not found redreſſe, our Kings have held the League as broken, and denounced Warre, or ſeiſed all the goods of the ſame Princes Subjects within England; and I dare ſay there have been more warres undertaken by our Princes, againſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain nations, onely for this cauſe, then for any one other cauſe whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Beſides, our Kings have in this caſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made uſe of that their Prerogative of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, either by prohibiting our Merchants from carrying our Commodities into thoſe parts, where they are charged with Impoſitions, that ſo by the want of our Commodities, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Princes might be enforced to abate their Impoſitions laid upon them, or by reſtraining the Merchants of forrain Princes to import or export commodities from hence; By which meanes forraine Princes have been compelled to deale favourably with our Merchants for the good of their owne Subjects; All theſe are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ordinary means to prevent or redreſſe
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:157030:75"/> the inconvenience which may grow by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of other Princes: If all theſe ordinary means ſhould happen to faile, which can hardly ſo fall out, and that the laying of Impoſitions be indeed the only means that is left to redreſſe the inconvenience, why ſhould not that be done by Act of Parliament as well in theſe times, as it was in 7.<hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. to take downe the Impoſition of Foure Ducates upon a But of Malmſey, impoſed by the Venetians, And as it was done by Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> the 19. yeere of her Reigne, to prevent the laying of Impoſitions by forraine Princes upon <hi>Salt-fiſh,</hi> as may appeare by the printed Statutes of 19. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 10. But as I have ſaid, the providence of the Prince, and ordinary power of reſtraint may very well meet with the inconvenience.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the chiefe reaſons made in mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of impoſitions, the weakneſſe of them, and their dangerous conſequence, you cannot but perceive; For by the ſame reaſons, Taxes within the Land, may be as well proved to be lawfull. On the contrary part, you have heard the reaſons againſt impoſitions fortified by many Records and Statutes in the point; So as I conclude, that <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> neither in the time of warre, or other the greateſt neceſſitie or occaſion that may be (much leſſe in the time of peace) neither upon forraine, nor inland Commodities of whatſoever nature, be they never ſo ſuperfluous or unneceſſary, neither up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:157030:76"/> Merchants, Strangers nor Denizens, may be laid by the Kings abſolute power, without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament, be it for never ſo ſhort a time, much leſſe to endure for ever, as ours. Though this be now my opinion, yet am not I ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate therein, but if yet I heare better reaſon, I will once againe change my minde; in the meane while, you ſee I had reaſon to alter my firſt: opinion, as being grounded upon very weak Reaſons, as now they appeare unto me. And ſo I ſuppoſe they doe alſo unto you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:157030:76"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Julii</hi> 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>AT a Committee of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for Examination of books, and of the Licenſing, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is Ordered, That this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon</hi> Impoſitions, <hi>be forthwith publiſhed in print.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>EDWARD DERING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
